<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mastiue, or Young-whelpe of the olde-dogge Epigrams and satyrs.</title>
            <author>Parrot, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114035</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849263</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849263</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14401</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14401)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1553:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mastiue, or Young-whelpe of the olde-dogge Epigrams and satyrs.</title>
                  <author>Parrot, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[70] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho: Creede, for Richard Meighen, and Thomas Iones, and are to be solde at S. Clements Church, without Temple-Barre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the vniuersall reader" signed: H.P., i.e. Henry Parrot.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>First word of title is xylographic.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>The date is cropped in most copies.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Satire, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Epigrams, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> MASTIVE, OR Young-Whelpe of the Olde-Dogge. </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epigrams and Satyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Horat:</bibl>
               <p>—Verba decent iratum plena minarum.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>Mondeo Mordentem</q>
               <figDesc>a mastiff dog with a banner in its mouth</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>The: Creede,</hi> for <hi>Richard Meighen,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Iones,</hi> and are to be ſolde at <hi>S. Clements</hi> Church, without Temple Rowe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VNIVERSALL <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle, or if Churliſh howſoeuer its no great matter, (though I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe there are not many amongſt you can be ſo dogged as will but offer to bite at me, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if ye knew how loath I would bee knowne to become your Debtors, aboue all others.) But to the purpoſe; I promiſed not long ſince, to buſie my ſelfe no more with theſe ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard kinde of commodities, mary t'was with a <hi>Prouiſo,</hi> vnles I otherwiſe were vrg'd by ſuch, as fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues perhaps agreeued, that I laſt forgot them, will now perforce incite mee therevnto, for more aſſured manifeſtation of my remembrance: Whome but to point at in particular, were to lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their imperfections, whoſe viler partes (for olde acquaintance) I rather may be thought to take pittie of: (and yet could I wiſh to haue your <hi>Clarke</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your
<hi>Sexton,</hi> by more then wearing a pen in his eare) <hi>Sed praeſtat tacere, ſuadeas.</hi> For any other more barbarous or fowle-mouthed
<hi>Mungrells,</hi> that haue bin lowder barking then the reſt: Ile not defile my hands by giuing ſuch the leaſt of chaſtiſement, <pb facs="tcp:14401:3"/>but leaue them peremptorily to the laſhing <hi>Dogge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whipper</hi> for thoſe <hi>Curres</hi> prouided.</p>
            <p>But now, may ſome guilty-conceited-<hi>Cooks-combe</hi> take himſelfe wilfully by the bottle-Noſe, ſaying: I ayme at him particularly; and ſo haue colour for what I doe.</p>
            <p>If any ſuch will needes ſo gald-backt prooue, as cannot chooſe but kick and wince without rubbing, or but at the ſound of a Curry-combe only, let them (by my conſent) bee ſadled for Iades, without dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, &amp; get the Scratches, till the <hi>Farrier</hi> giue them ouer. In briefe, I would be thought as guiltleſſe of blaming, as I was careleſſe of the lines compoſing: Which if they pleaſe; why ſo: if otherwiſe, I will not warrant them to bee better worth: and ſo Fare-well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="in_place_of_encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:3"/>
            <head>Author pro ſeipſo.</head>
            <l>LOoke nought for heere of Writers commendation:</l>
            <l>Ile not be thought one of their Fauour-winners:</l>
            <l>Which would to Lameneſſe ſeeme but ſupportation,</l>
            <l>Or as an Offering made for Young-Beginners.</l>
            <l>Who knowes not, Tauernes painted Poſts, and Signes,</l>
            <l>Are but th' attractiues to deceitfull wines?</l>
         </div>
         <div type="instruction_to_printer">
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:4"/>
            <head>Ad Bibliopolam.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>PRinter or Stationer, or what ere thou prooue,</l>
               <l>Shalt mee record to Times poſteritie:</l>
               <l>Ile not enioyne thee, but request in loue,</l>
               <l>Thou ſo much deigne my Booke to dignifie;</l>
               <l>As firſt it bee not with your Ballads mixt,</l>
               <l>Next, not at Play-houſes, mongst Pippins ſolde:</l>
               <l>Then that on Paſts, by th' Eares it ſtand not fixt,</l>
               <l>For euery dull-Mechanicke to beholde.</l>
               <l>Laſt, that it come not brought in Pedlers packs,</l>
               <l>To common Fayres, of Countrey, Towne, or Cittie:</l>
               <l>Solde at a Booth mongst Pinnes and Almanacks;</l>
               <l>Yet on thy hands to lye, thoult' ſay tw'er pittie;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let it be rather for Tobacco rent,</l>
               <l>Or Butchers-Wiues, next Clenſing-weeke in Lent.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="epigrams">
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> EPIGRAMS.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>A CVLINA AD CVRIAM.</head>
               <l>LIXA, that long a ſeruile Groome hath beene,</l>
               <l>Will now no more the man be knowne or ſeene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And reaſon good, he hath that place reſign'd,</l>
               <l>Witneſſe his Cloake throughout with veluet lin'd:</l>
               <l>Which by a Parradox comes thus to paſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The greazie Gull is turn'd a gallant Aſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Fiant, quae fata volunt.</head>
               <l>ASke ſwaggring <hi>Saltus,</hi> Why he beares ſuch ſway?</l>
               <l>He'll anſwere thus; <hi>Things muſt be as they may.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aske, How he comes ſo drunken day by day?</l>
               <l>Againe ſayes he, <hi>Things muſt be as they may.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aske him the reaſon, Why no debts he'll pay?</l>
               <l>The ſame replies, <hi>Things muſt be as they may.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aske, Why ſo ſeldome he deſires to pray?</l>
               <l>Still he concludes, <hi>Things muſt be as they may.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus ſee you <hi>Saltus</hi> nothing elſe will ſay;</l>
               <l>Should he be damn'd, <hi>It muſt be as it may.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Tempus edax rerum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>HEywood</hi> was held for <hi>Epigrams</hi> the beſt,</l>
               <l>What time old <hi>Church-yard</hi> dealt in verſe and proſe</l>
               <l>But faſhions ſince are growne out of requeſt,</l>
               <l>As Bombaſt-Dublets, Baſes, and Round-hoſe.</l>
               <l>Or as your Lady, may it now be ſaide,</l>
               <l>That looks leſſe louely then her <hi>Chamber-maide.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:5"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Foemina; Quid non?</head>
               <l>WHat dares <hi>Gallantus</hi> for his Wench not doe?</l>
               <l>Though it concerne the hazard of his necke:</l>
               <l>Aske what ſhee will, or haue a minde vnto,</l>
               <l>He ſtreight procures, and brings her at a becke.</l>
               <l>Bid him goe rob a Gold-ſmiths ſhoppe for Plate,</l>
               <l>Stabbe him that calls her by the name of Puncke;</l>
               <l>Beate Conſtables, or Watch for walking late,</l>
               <l>Vndoe a Bawde, or make a Pander druncke:</l>
               <l>In briefe what is't, that may to pleaſure wooe,</l>
               <l>But braue <hi>Gallantus</hi> for his wench durſt doo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Leui, leuiora.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MAdam Fenestra,</hi> fearfull of her Dyet,</l>
               <l>Feeds by no meanes on fleſh that's tough or olde:</l>
               <l>Which brings her queazie ſtomacke out of quiet,</l>
               <l>And therefore pickes on pureſt can be ſolde;</l>
               <l>Of leaſt-growne Lamb, and tendreſt Beefe that's bigge,</l>
               <l>The whiteſt Cow-calfe, and the youngſt Sow-pigge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To Iohn of Paules Church-yarde.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>TO</hi> thee <hi>(Braue Iohn)</hi> my booke I dedicate,</l>
               <l>That wilt from <hi>A-Iax,</hi> with thy force defend it:</l>
               <l>And counterchecke each <hi>Cocks-combs</hi> ſpleen and hate,</l>
               <l>That not good language, or good lookes ſhall lend it.</l>
               <l>Thou placed art as <hi>Sentinell,</hi> to quaile</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſecret Foes, our dangers ſhall pretend:</l>
               <l>Making their Top-ſailes, Flagges, and Bonnets vaile,</l>
               <l>Like to the <hi>Blocke-houſe</hi> ouer-gainſt
<hi>Graueſ-ende.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And to conclude, mauger their worſt of ſpite,</l>
               <l>Durſt bidde the proudeſt of them all goe—</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:5"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Subitò responſio leui.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Doctor</hi> being ask't what meanes he knew,</l>
               <l>Were ſuch as beſt to opening <hi>Phyſicke</hi> drew:</l>
               <l>He not to ſeeke, for ſudden anſwer ſayes,</l>
               <l>Ther's nothing better then a <hi>Bunch of kayes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Animoſus, pediculoſus.</head>
               <l>MATHO from Sea hath ſuch a purchaſe brought,</l>
               <l>As is not frequent, or of each man ſought:</l>
               <l>Which to divulgate, <hi>Matho</hi> proues not nice,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing, God damne him, but Out-landiſh Lice.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Detur quod meritum.</head>
               <l>SOTVS muſt now prooue Checquer Clarke at leaſt,</l>
               <l>That therto hath bin trayn'd twelue yeeres &amp; more:</l>
               <l>Nay, in good ſadneſſe, hee's much more increaſt,</l>
               <l>Conſidering what he hath beene heretofore:</l>
               <l>Why may not <hi>Sotus</hi> then in caſe ſo cleere,</l>
               <l>Boldly demand his Calues head euery yeere?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Secreta noſtra nobis.</head>
               <l>TASSVS from Temple Stayres by water goes</l>
               <l>To Weſtminſter, and backe to Temple rowes:</l>
               <l>Belike he loues not trot too much the ſtreete,</l>
               <l>Or ſurbait on the ſtones his tender feete:</l>
               <l>Tut come, there's ſomething in't muſt not be knowne:</l>
               <l>But Sir, beleeu't, <hi>The debt is not his owne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:6"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Tua logice noſtra.</head>
               <l>LVCAS on's Lady layes a foule obiection,</l>
               <l>Saying ſhe weareth not her owne complexion.</l>
               <l>But then her Ladyſhip may ſay he lyeth,</l>
               <l>Is't not her owne I pray you which ſhe buyeth?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus promptos facit.</head>
               <l>RACHEL at firſt would rayle vpon her man,</l>
               <l>That ſcarce knew how to beare himſelf before her:</l>
               <l>Nor almoſt which way looke or hold her Fan,</l>
               <l>But now (thanks Fortune) finely can come o're her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Si nihil attuleris ibis, &amp;c.</head>
               <l>WAT told his wife how much he late had ſtraid,</l>
               <l>Yet faine would <hi>notwithſtanding</hi> pardoned be:</l>
               <l>To whom ſhe ragingly replyde and ſaid,</l>
               <l>Think'ſt with not ſtanding (Slaue) to anſwere me?</l>
               <l>Hath then your <hi>Pinnace</hi> in thoſe Ports beene landing,</l>
               <l>And now puts in prouiſoes, <hi>notwithſtanding?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Indomitis ferendum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MArtinus</hi> ouermuch commends his mare</l>
               <l>To be the beſt man ere layd legge vpon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Wer't not for one defect (a fault that's rare)</l>
               <l>Shee's onely ſubiect to obliuion:</l>
               <l>That ſtumbling headlong in her courſe amaine,</l>
               <l>So ſoone forgets, as downe ſhe falles againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:6"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Tempora promoribus.</head>
               <l>PLucke off your Bonnet, you Sir in the feather,</l>
               <l>And learne to know when Officers paſſe by:</l>
               <l>Thinke you all men hayle fellowes met together?</l>
               <l>You would be taught to be more mannerly.</l>
               <l>Tut, ſay you knew him nere ſo well before,</l>
               <l>Will that be now excuſe ſufficient?</l>
               <l>Or ſay his pleaſure be to keepe a whore,</l>
               <l>Dare you preſume he liues incontinent?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non nosti Summis vitium preualet?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et omne maius minus continet?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Domi, &amp; foras Idem.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CIuis</hi> at Court being lately bid to dinner,</l>
               <l>Had thought to make his ſtomacke loſt a winner:</l>
               <l>But ſitting downe when each had tane his place,</l>
               <l>The meat was gone ere <hi>Ciuis</hi> could ſay Grace.</l>
               <l>Whereat quoth he, a man may boldly ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From hence the rich are emptie ſent away.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Plus Canis ictus amat.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CReta</hi> that cloſely could her ſecrets couer,</l>
               <l>Fain'd to be iealous of her loathed Spouſe;</l>
               <l>Which he beleeu'd (God wot) &amp; more did loue her,</l>
               <l>Preſuming, <hi>London</hi> not her like allowes.</l>
               <l>Well, goe thy wayes (thought I) hold on thy trade,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th'art euen the trueſt he whom God nere made.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Roſa omnibus olet.</head>
               <l>ROSE is a fayre, but not a proper woman:</l>
               <l>Can any creature proper be, that's common?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:7"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Caelat ſua crimina Sanctis.</head>
               <l>CVRTA hath now no colour or euaſion,</l>
               <l>To meete or frolicke as time late permitted,</l>
               <l>Becauſe her husband barres vp all occaſion,</l>
               <l>That for ſuch pleaſures and aduantage fitted:</l>
               <l>Keepes her from going to her childe at nurſe,</l>
               <l>Denyes acceſſe vnto her Garden-houſe:</l>
               <l>For which ſhee giues him many a bitter curſe,</l>
               <l>And ſweares, ſhe not eſteemes his threats a Louſe.</l>
               <l>The beſt eſcape her cunning can deuiſe,</l>
               <l>Is once a weeke to <hi>Blacke-fryers</hi> exerciſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Curanda primum praeſentia.</head>
               <l>LETTICE that late was ſo reſolu'd to marry,</l>
               <l>On more aduice will now this tweluemonth tarry:</l>
               <l>How ſhould ſhe ſooner elſe indeed diſpoſe</l>
               <l>Of the young Baſtard wherewithall ſhe goes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Latot Anguis in herba.</head>
               <l>WHen Capring-<hi>Coſmo</hi> comes from dauncing Schoole,</l>
               <l>He firſt commaunds the Maide pluck off his Hoſe:</l>
               <l>Next bids her bring a Cuſhion and a ſtoole,</l>
               <l>On which (ſhe kneeling) rubbes his feete and toes.</l>
               <l>That done, hee calls for's night-cap and his gowne,</l>
               <l>Fearing the colde might catch him vnaware;</l>
               <l>Nor more will walke forth (ſayes) that day in towne,</l>
               <l>Whence you may geſſe, he hath no Coine to ſpare.</l>
               <l>But that's not it, <hi>Coſmo</hi> to bed is gone,</l>
               <l>Cauſing his ſhirt be waſht that hath but one.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:7"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Manus manum fricat.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>BAlbus</hi> his Tennants will no more pay rent,</l>
               <l>Till for their wiues he firſt giue them content:</l>
               <l>Is't reaſon <hi>Balbus</hi> without Coyne disburſing,</l>
               <l>Get them with childe, and nere allow for Nurſing?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Grauè Condimentum, &amp;c.</head>
               <l>TWo Goſſips lately in contention grewe,</l>
               <l>Which of the twaine liu'de greateſt in eſteeme:</l>
               <l>And leſſe the ſubſtance of the other knewe,</l>
               <l>Whereby her credit might the better ſeeme.</l>
               <l>Quoth one of them, t'is knowne my charge is ſuch,</l>
               <l>In vineger and muſtard euery yeare:</l>
               <l>Indeed quoth th'other I ſuppos'd aſmuch,</l>
               <l>What a deuowring ſaucie Drabbe you were;</l>
               <l>But (which is worſe) I heare your Neighbours talke,</l>
               <l>The skore runnes yet with Chandlers on the chalke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Belluinus quotidianus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DAcus</hi> approues, and ſtoutly ſtands vpon it,</l>
               <l>Thers not a man in <hi>Middleſex</hi> out drinks him:</l>
               <l>And thereto dares he lay all's ſubſtance on it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Hee breathes not mortall, one to one that ſincks him.</l>
               <l>For Sir beleeu't, there's no day comes about,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Dacus</hi> drinks himſelfe a <hi>Hogs-Head</hi> out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>¶ <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, ſi des mutuo.</head>
               <l>WHen <hi>Dicke</hi> wants money, he deſires to borowe,</l>
               <l>No more then (da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me him) hee'l repay to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:8"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Doceat experientia.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>KAte</hi> ſtill complaynes her Mother doth her wrong,</l>
               <l>Cauſing her keepe her mayden-head ſo long:</l>
               <l>For iudge (quoth ſhe) your ſelfe, if at my ſtature</l>
               <l>You felt not then the fame inſtinct of nature!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Non propria, quae Maribus.</head>
               <l>SAy <hi>Beſſe</hi> (quoth <hi>Brutus</hi>) if thou loue me, ſo;</l>
               <l>If not, why ſo: tuſh <hi>Brutus,</hi> thus much know:</l>
               <l>Since ſhe to loue in Common firſt began,</l>
               <l>She lou'd not thee: thou art no Common man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Non omnibus idem.</head>
               <l>YOung <hi>Lalus</hi> deales on light commodities,</l>
               <l>Of choyſeſt Gyrles he ſafely can bring forth:</l>
               <l>But yet reſpectleſſe proues to peoples eyes,</l>
               <l>As if he were ſome great mans ſonne of worth.</l>
               <l>Conſorts with Gallants, ſtands on's reputation,</l>
               <l>Eates of the beſt and daintieſt can be ſold:</l>
               <l>Scornes to be ranckt with men of occupation,</l>
               <l>That are not Gentiles like himſelfe enrold.</l>
               <l>Aske how he liues; hee tels the vulgar ſort,</l>
               <l>By play, by knowledge, trauell and commerce,</l>
               <l>Of which he makes a ſad and long report,</l>
               <l>Which they thinke ſimply, without more reherſe:</l>
               <l>But to the wiſe and worthy vnderſtander,</l>
               <l>He proſtrate proues your priuate ſports-Commander.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Omnia tempus habent.</head>
               <l>HOw comes it <hi>Doll</hi> liues ſo demure of late,</l>
               <l>That whilome vs'd to frollicke with her friends?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:8"/>
               <l>Oh, ſhe hath chang'd it ſeemes her former ſtate,</l>
               <l>And to be ciuill for awhile intends:</l>
               <l>Would any mad Wench preſently on mariage,</l>
               <l>Proue her ſelfe pack-horſe for each common carriage?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Irati, Implacabiles.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DIcke</hi> with his Dogs in ſuch an outrage grew,</l>
               <l>As which was next him he to hanging drew:</l>
               <l>Who looking fearefull, faine would backwards gather<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nay, vp thou goeſt</hi> (<hi>quoth</hi> Dicke) <hi>and th'wert my Father.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Tempus edaxrerum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FLaminio</hi> weares an euerlaſting Sute,</l>
               <l>That would (ſaith he) all Faſhions yet confute:</l>
               <l>Wer't not ſo greazy, and ſo ſtaind with Wine,</l>
               <l>Which he hath dropt vpon ſince ninetie nine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>In cauda venenum.</head>
               <l>THat <hi>Finch</hi> the Gold-ſmith hath a fayre young wife,</l>
               <l>It needs no doubt; ther's none but might her loue:</l>
               <l>Then wer't not ſhame and pitty of her life,</l>
               <l>If from a Gold-Finch ſhe a Wag-taile proue?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nemo omnibus horis ſapit.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cullus,</hi> carefull of his reputation,</l>
               <l>Choſe euermore your priuat'ſt ſporting houſe:</l>
               <l>Which leaſt might bring his name in defamation,</l>
               <l>Or to ſucceeding times proue dangerous:</l>
               <l>But ſee how well he could occaſions quench,</l>
               <l>And yet be taken with a Begger-wench.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:9"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Multi videntur &amp; non ſunt.</head>
               <l>CAll <hi>Clinias Coward,</hi> he outragious than;</l>
               <l>Dares to aduenture life with any man.</l>
               <l>Prouided he be not's ſuperiour,</l>
               <l>His vnderling or baſe inferiour,</l>
               <l>Nor yet his fellow: for ſaith <hi>Clinias,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should any of theſe euils come to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Tis ten to one the quarrell neuer ends;</l>
               <l>If I kill him, hee'l kill me by his friends.</l>
               <l>Or if my Vaſſall; conqueſt is not much,</l>
               <l>Anoble minde diſdaines to fight with ſuch:</l>
               <l>And if my fellow; Wiſedome tells too late,</l>
               <l>True fellowſhip conſiſts in Loue, not hate:</l>
               <l>Bring <hi>Clinias</hi> one that is not of theſe three,</l>
               <l>And then to fight ther's none ſo bold as he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Fruſtravocaueris Heri.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DIcke</hi> had but two words to maintaine him euer,</l>
               <l>And that was <hi>Stand,</hi> and after Stand,
<hi>Deliuer;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>Dick's</hi> in <hi>New-gate,</hi> and hee feares ſhall neuer,</l>
               <l>Be bleſt againe, with that ſweete word <hi>Deliuer.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Poſt gaudia luctus.</head>
               <l>THree Trades-men &amp; their wiues went all to
<hi>Douer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſee the Monuments of <hi>Iulius Caeſar:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From whence to <hi>Paris</hi> would they next poſt ouer,</l>
               <l>And not diſſwaded be by King nor Keyſar:</l>
               <l>But ſpent two hundred pounds on idle motions,</l>
               <l>That now in Ludgate liue by mens deuotions.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Rumpit ſuo pondere pordus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>IAne</hi> from the Iuſtice cannot be acquitted,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Sonne hath deeply vpon her committed.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:9"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Filius ex puluere Patris.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MIlo</hi> grew ſicke becauſe his Dad left giuing,</l>
               <l>In which conſumption he had dyed out-right,</l>
               <l>Had not his death at laſt put him in liuing,</l>
               <l>By which good fortune he is dub'd a Knight.</l>
               <l>Vnhappy Sonne, to draw that vitall breath,</l>
               <l>Who like a Pellican liu'ſt by his death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>In Zoylum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>ZOylus,</hi> I heare you take my Rymes in ſnuffe,</l>
               <l>Crie fie, t'ls Ribaldrie, or ſome ſuch ſtuffe:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Zoylus</hi> know, I ſcorne to deale with you;</l>
               <l>He writes foule ſtuffe that treates of your baſe crewe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>era filia Patris.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>WHy</hi> ſtriues young <hi>Gallatèa,</hi> for the wall?</l>
               <l>If needs you'l know the cauſe (qd. one) you ſhall:</l>
               <l>Her Father was a <hi>Maeſon,</hi> and they ſay,</l>
               <l>It makes her Ladyſhip leane much that way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Cupiens culpare, neſcit.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DOrus</hi> diſdaines theſe <hi>Epigrams</hi> I make,</l>
               <l>Saying they ſauour not of ought that's in them:</l>
               <l>Nay, which is more then that, hee'll vndertake</l>
               <l>They are but ſtinking ſtuffe ere you begin them:</l>
               <l>And yet before (quoth he) they fauour'd not:</l>
               <l>See how the buzzard talkes he knowes not what!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Malium optanti gratum.</head>
               <l>A Wanton Dame that of her Spouſe repented,</l>
               <l>(Becauſe he would her now and then diſpleaſe,)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:10"/>
               <l>Was told by one (which made her much contented)</l>
               <l>That he was hang'd or drown'd beyond the Seas:</l>
               <l>Who dreading nought, ask't what might worſe enſue,</l>
               <l>For this ſhe thought was too good to be true.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ireſcit curua Senectus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CLaudus</hi> with age and ſicknes long declining,</l>
               <l>That had a Letcher bene in time of yore:</l>
               <l>Spying a Laſſe paſſe by him; ſpake thus whyning,</l>
               <l>To one that led him, <hi>There's a luſty Whore.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Commune diuerſorium Meritrix.</head>
               <l>IF <hi>Phoedra</hi> were but halfe ſo chaſte as faire,</l>
               <l>So kinde as coye, and but ſo wiſe as wittie:</l>
               <l>Shee would the ruines of her Houſe repaire,</l>
               <l>That rent and torne, lye proſtrate neere the Cittie.</l>
               <l>Where all that trauell, and are come from farre,</l>
               <l>May freely enter without bolt or barre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Saltim videri cupit.</head>
               <l>SIgnior <hi>Fantaſmo</hi> that Capricious youth,</l>
               <l>Poſting to <hi>London,</hi> lights vpon theſe Rimes:</l>
               <l>And tells the Stationer for ſimple truth,</l>
               <l>They are but froth and excrements of times.</l>
               <l>Who for his purpoſe no ſuch <hi>Pamphet</hi> needed;</l>
               <l>And (but an <hi>Aſſe</hi>) had long ere now proceeded.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Fruſtràlaues Aethiopum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>POntus</hi> that poore and quondam ſcuruie Scribe,</l>
               <l>Rays'd from the ruſt of rude raſcallitie:</l>
               <l>Now proling prooues the proudeſt of his Tribe,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill a Cullion will he liue and die.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:10"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Ex ouibus opes.</head>
               <l>THat <hi>Notus</hi> ſhould ſo neerely liue twas ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Who died the richeſt Marchant vs'd the Exchange:</l>
               <l>Yet on the matter was no Marchant nether,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ſubſtance came by Sheepe-skinnes altogether.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Domina dominatur Ancillae.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MAud</hi> with inceſſant termes reuiles her maid,</l>
               <l>Haſt not bene warnd (qd. ſhe) of this before?</l>
               <l>How oft haue I this geere vppon thee laid,</l>
               <l>Say; Canſt deny't? Art not an arrand whore?</l>
               <l>Yes (qd. the Maid) forſooth it's partly true,</l>
               <l>Elſe ſhould I be more honeſt thought then you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Admoniti foelices.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MAtura</hi> wearie of the Countrie life,</l>
               <l>Complaines her Husband nere to <hi>London</hi> brought her:</l>
               <l>That hath this twelue-month prou'd his honeſt wife,</l>
               <l>And not conſented ſcarce to one that ſought her.</l>
               <l>But bids him roundly herewith looke vnto it,</l>
               <l>Be hee a Tinker next that comes ſhall doe it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Cauſidici non ſemper beati.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>LEntus</hi> the Lawyer prayes the Terme were ended,</l>
               <l>That hath not for this fortnight got one Fee:</l>
               <l>Nor ought effected as his hopes intended,</l>
               <l>And yet in Commons muſt for cuſtome bee:</l>
               <l>But if his takings ſtill proue ſuch as theſe,</l>
               <l>Let them (qd. <hi>Lentus</hi>) packe to <hi>Hell</hi> that pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:11"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Stant quae probatae.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>GOrgonius</hi> ſurfet may with cordiall food,</l>
               <l>Able, reuiue him, and reſtore his blood:</l>
               <l>But alls in vaine, no Phiſicks Art will doe it,</l>
               <l>His wife 'fore any Doctor dares ſtand to it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Funis multorum Finis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>LAniſta</hi> many Sonnes adopted had,</l>
               <l>Whome ſtill he vs'de to title as his owne:</l>
               <l>And they as duely likewiſe call'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> him <hi>Dad,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But were on ſudden all diſperſt vnknowne.</l>
               <l>Till when <hi>Lanista</hi> walking <hi>Holborne,</hi> ſpide,</l>
               <l>Two of his Broode in Carts for <hi>Tyborne</hi> bound:</l>
               <l>Who to their <hi>Syre</hi> with woefull Farwell cride,</l>
               <l>No more may wee <hi>your Sonnes</hi> on earth be found.</l>
               <l>Yea (qd. <hi>Lanista</hi>) goes that way the game?</l>
               <l>I knew not erſt what of <hi>my Sonnes</hi> became.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Durum telum neceſſitas.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>LAurence</hi> his light and late made Sommer-weede,</l>
               <l>Will now this winter ſtand him in no ſteed:</l>
               <l>But muſt be forthwith forſt, though nere ſo loath,</l>
               <l>To chop with Brokers for a ſute of cloath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Ebria, minus curioſa.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xurio</hi> to accompliſh his deſire,</l>
               <l>Makes his <hi>Wench</hi> drunke, would you the cauſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire?</l>
               <l>Hee's ſo deformd, as not a common-Punck,</l>
               <l>But would deteſt him, if ſhee were not drunck.</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:11"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Charae nimis voluptas.</head>
               <l>SYr <hi>Ralphe</hi> reſolues to leaue this Coourt-like ſtate,</l>
               <l>And liue i'th Countrey at a lower rate:</l>
               <l>Is it not reaſon he be cloſe and neare,</l>
               <l>That hath but bare one hundred marks a yeare?</l>
               <l>Beſides the money which his Knight-hood ſpent him,</l>
               <l>Not yet repaide, that ſo long ſince was lent him?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Tempora, Mores.</head>
               <l>IN <hi>Times</hi> of yore, was neither <hi>Bond</hi> nor
<hi>Bill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For each would then his word, by word fulfill:</l>
               <l>Till when crept in this ſtrange <hi>Catastrophe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As ſome for conformation, wrote <hi>Per me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which now ſay Scriueners, <hi>non est ita mos,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It muſt be <hi>Noueriut per preſentes nos.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nuptiae post Nummos.</head>
               <l>THere was a <hi>Time</hi> when Men for loue did marrie,</l>
               <l>And not for Lucre ſake, as now we ſee:</l>
               <l>Which from that former Age ſo much doth varie,</l>
               <l>As all's for what youl giue? or nought muſt bee.</l>
               <l>So that this ancient word call'd <hi>Matrimony,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is whollie made <hi>A matter now of Mony.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Sero vocaberis Heri.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ke</hi> that in <hi>Lattine</hi> lately ſcorn'd to looke,</l>
               <l>Would now read <hi>Engliſh,</hi> might hee haue his booke.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:12"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Tonſores minus ditiores.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>thert</hi> admires how Lawyers get ſo much,</l>
               <l>And that his commings in ſhould not be ſuch:</l>
               <l>Who hath beene knowne a Poler and a Shauer</l>
               <l>Theſe fortie yeers, yet nere could proue a Sauer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Sublata cauſa tollitur, &amp;c.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MArcus</hi> hath all madde companie forſworne,</l>
               <l>All ſorts of of wine, all womens vaine enticing:</l>
               <l>All exerciſe, all pleaſures quite forborne;</l>
               <l>All hunting, hawking, bowling, carding, dicing,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Purſe</hi> (the maine of all) hath tane infection,</l>
               <l>And all that <hi>Doll</hi> can doe moues no erection.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Pro cauſa vt ſuprà.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>GAlfridus</hi> takes <hi>Tobacco</hi> all in ſnuffe,</l>
               <l>Who nere could any from his noſthrills puffe;</l>
               <l>Since the <hi>Low-Countrey-warres</hi> of late conſign'd him,</l>
               <l>To leaue at leaſt his <hi>Smelling-ſenſe</hi> behind him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Ebrius diſſimulans.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>BAttus</hi> (though bound from drinking wine of late)</l>
               <l>Can thus farre with his Oath equiuocate:</l>
               <l>He will not drinke, and yet be drunke ere noone,</l>
               <l>His manner is to eate it with a ſpoone.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:12"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Tandem potiuntur Achiui.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zanthus</hi> was zealous bent, but could not pleaſe</l>
               <l>His Ladie <hi>Miſtreſſe,</hi> he ſo long had ſerued:</l>
               <l>Nor by his beſt attendance once, but eaſe</l>
               <l>Or ſtay his ſtomacke, if he ſhould haue ſtarued.</l>
               <l>Till forſt with Famine, found her in that ſnare,</l>
               <l>Which ſince to ſilence <hi>Zanthus</hi> takes his ſhare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Fronti, nulla fides.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DOll</hi> in diſdaine, doth from her heeles defie,</l>
               <l>The beſt that breathes ſhall tell her blacks her eye:</l>
               <l>A and that it's true ſhee ſpeaks, who can ſay nay?</l>
               <l>When none that lookes on't, but will ſweare t'is gray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Minus domi Hyſtriones.</head>
               <l>MIſtreſſe <hi>Fardella</hi> feard ſhee ſhould conceiue,</l>
               <l>Before the time in wedlocke ſtate could linck her:</l>
               <l>Which would <hi>Fardellas</hi> fortunes quite bereaue,</l>
               <l>Therefore reſolu'd, on ſudden doth bethinck her.</l>
               <l>Gainſt when the Midwife might in child-bed lay her,</l>
               <l>To ſhrowde a while, for ſhelter with a Player.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nondum Doemone dignus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>TAgus</hi> was told had got the Diuell and all,</l>
               <l>In that his ſubſtance did ſo much excell:</l>
               <l>It may (qd. <hi>Tagus</hi>) proue in time I ſhall,</l>
               <l>Get what's ſufficient, though not thriue ſo well.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:13"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Non ſemper inſcipiens.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>KEſter</hi> can court his Miſtreſſe, would you knew it,</l>
               <l>Weare hanſom cloaths, pledge healths, or breake a ieſt;</l>
               <l>Drink drunke with any man, &amp; neuer ſpue it,</l>
               <l>Or take <hi>Tobacco</hi> with the prowdſt and beſt.</l>
               <l>Had they but kept him one ye are more at's Grammer,</l>
               <l>You ſhould haue found him then no <hi>Ninthammer.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Laudes cùm labe.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CAius</hi> commends his Siſter many wayes,</l>
               <l>To be the myrror of admired praiſe:</l>
               <l>Wert not for two foule reaſons that enſue,</l>
               <l>Shee's ſomtimes drunck, and playes the double (w.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Fas per inſcipientem.</head>
               <l>WHo dares ſay <hi>Doltus</hi> ſpeaketh barbariſme,</l>
               <l>That ſchollerlike can make a <hi>Syllogiſme?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can cap a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> which may deſerue commend,</l>
               <l>And hath his <hi>Grammer rules</hi> at's fingers ende.</l>
               <l>Can write a Piſtell to his <hi>Dad</hi> in
<hi>Lattin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And one day hopes to weare a ſute of Sattin.</l>
               <l>Yea, make his mother bleſt that ere ſhee bore him,</l>
               <l>For of his age, fewe yet haue gone before him:</l>
               <l>I meane for Tallnes of his lymbs and bone,</l>
               <l>At graſſe time next, full grown to twenty one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Experientia nimis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>WAt</hi> will no more in Wedlocke bands be tyde,</l>
               <l>That thereof hath too much experience tryde:</l>
               <l>And durſt a Noble to a nutſhell wage,</l>
               <l>The next Wife makes him fall in ſurpluſage.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:13"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Non omnia pꝰſſumus omues.</head>
               <l>THough <hi>Petrus</hi> nere could <hi>Epigrams</hi> compoſe,</l>
               <l>Not is your perfect <hi>Poêts</hi> Imitator:</l>
               <l>Yet well the world may ſee he writes in <hi>Proſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergò</hi> no Cobler, but a true
<hi>Tranſlator.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nequicquam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>encri verba.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>WIll</hi> wooes his wench with wordes of
<hi>Eloquence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Praying he might her corps enthalamize:</l>
               <l>And of his loue impart that influence,</l>
               <l>Which with her liking beſt may ſimpathize.</l>
               <l>She, who regardleſſe at his ſpeech doth ſpurne,</l>
               <l>Saith; T'is not words of Art muſt ſerue her turne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Optimus in peſſimis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>VAleſco</hi> mounts vpon the wings of Fame,</l>
               <l>For an admyr'd report and matchles name:</l>
               <l>That Courting can convince your coyeſt Punck,</l>
               <l>And drinck e're midnight healths yet not be drunck.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Diaboli poenitentes.</head>
               <l>COme; What ſhall's doe (qd. <hi>Ned</hi>) this afternoone?</l>
               <l>That hath at <hi>Noddy</hi> neither loſt nor wonne:</l>
               <l>Theres not a Play (ſaith hee) worth looking on,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Mistris Moll</hi> from <hi>Clarkenwell</hi> is gone.</l>
               <l>Troth let's doo once what no man would coniecture,</l>
               <l>Turne honeſt for an houre, and heare a Lecture.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:14"/>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra poſſe negatur.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>HIstrix</hi> hath felt himſelfe long ill at eaſe,</l>
               <l>But thereof durſt not to the world complaine;</l>
               <l>Hoping the times would all things well appeaſe,</l>
               <l>And eke reſtore his former health againe,</l>
               <l>But t'would not doe: ſo that perforce aduizde.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hiſtrix</hi> (God help him) muſt be circumcis'de.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Infirmis experientia.</head>
               <l>OLd <hi>Creſus</hi> ſtands vpon his tackling ſtout,</l>
               <l>He can as well as ere hee cold hould out:</l>
               <l>To whome his wife ſayes, men may laugh that win,</l>
               <l>Pray tell me Syr, <hi>Can you as well hold in?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iliora <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tiliora.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>POdrus</hi> but practiz'd when he firſt was young,</l>
               <l>To write and reade, and caſt vp ſome Accounts:</l>
               <l>Nor cares a louſe (ſaith he) for th' <hi>Lattine</hi> tongue,</l>
               <l>Which would not gaine him halfe that now amounts.</l>
               <l>For if (qd. <hi>Podrus</hi>) <hi>Shoo-makers</hi> excell,</l>
               <l>Why may not then our Coblers doe as well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Qui Latrans, modo mordens.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>BLandus</hi> I heare will proue a <hi>Byter</hi> knowne,</l>
               <l>That gently vs'd of late to fawne and cogge:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Blandus</hi> then, be ſuch a byter growne,</l>
               <l>What kinne is <hi>Blandus</hi> to <hi>my Maſtyf-dogge?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:14"/>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuit vt edat.</head>
               <l>WHen <hi>Gluto</hi> goes to dine at th'Ordinarie,</l>
               <l>To ſlay his ſtomacke eates a cruſt and drinks:</l>
               <l>Then call's for victuals, ſweares he cannot tary,</l>
               <l>Which till it comes, a month each minute thinks:</l>
               <l>Then ſits him downe, and takes the higheſt place,</l>
               <l>Puts ſalt on's Trencher, cuts a loafe in twayne,</l>
               <l>And nere remembers ought of ſaying Grace,</l>
               <l>The ſight of meate ſo captiuates his brayne:</l>
               <l>Whereto he lurching, ſo about him layes,</l>
               <l>As muſt ſuffice him for at leaſt two dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Stimulat, ignota Cupdo.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>SVſan,</hi> for ſpight ſhe could not be eſpouz'd</l>
               <l>Before her Siſter, who is three yeeres younger,</l>
               <l>Reſolu'd her ſelfe at laſt, from dulneſſe rouz'd,</l>
               <l>To tell her Mother ſhe could ſtay no longer;</l>
               <l>Nor all this while her time had ſo miſpent,</l>
               <l>But that ſhe knew no ſooner what it meant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Opinio maior Veritate.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>IEnkin</hi> that iealous liu'd without deſerts,</l>
               <l>Was told by one his Wife had worthy parts:</l>
               <l>At which he ten times more outragious ſwore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How ſhould her parts be knowne, ſhe not a ( )</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Aperit ſua crimina ſomnis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>IVdith</hi> is growne (God bleſſe her) ſuch a Bride,</l>
               <l>For face and feature, and in truth excells:</l>
               <l>Worthy to ſolace by the beſt mans ſide,</l>
               <l>Throughout that Streete and Pariſh where ſhe dwells:</l>
               <l>Wer't not for one defect, confounds all this,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She vſeth nightly in her bed to</hi>—.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:15"/>
            <lg>
               <head>In Roſa Spina.</head>
               <l>YOung Miſtriſſe <hi>Ioice</hi> is, without ieſting, fayre;</l>
               <l>How can ſhe chooſe, hauing a flexen hayre?</l>
               <l>A necke ſo white, and a more pleaſing eye</l>
               <l>Then any Wench you <hi>lightly</hi> can eſpie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide, tace.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>SEruus</hi> hath ſeene his Ladies ſecrecies,</l>
               <l>Which for his eares he durſt not patronize,</l>
               <l>Much leſſe preſume to make leaſt enterprize,</l>
               <l>Onely to whiſtle may the tune ſuffice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Non ſuo ſe pendebit Capiſtro.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PAulus</hi> no Purſe about him loues to cary,</l>
               <l>Leaſt to himſelfe he ſhould prooue acceſſarie,</l>
               <l>For much ſpent charges, which were meerely loſt,</l>
               <l>Knowing he ſhall be drunke at others coſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Suam nouit Infirmitatem.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>IOſephus</hi> crau'd he might haue conference</l>
               <l>With <hi>Parnell</hi> in her chamber all alone;</l>
               <l>But <hi>Parnell</hi> pray'd ſhe might therein diſpence,</l>
               <l>For in her chamber muſt ſhe talke with none:</l>
               <l>Partly through feare ſhe ſhould be won with pelfe,</l>
               <l>But moſt becauſe ſhe durſt not truſt her ſelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:15"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Hoc proprium nobis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FRancis</hi> hath got a vaine and fooliſh vſe,</l>
               <l>Practiz'd ſo long, as now he cannot leaue it;</l>
               <l>Which grew at firſt by being too profuſe</l>
               <l>In his expences, (ſo you muſt conceiue it:)</l>
               <l>For well the reckning may you pay without him,</l>
               <l>So ſeldome beares he purſe or coyne about him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Huic habeo non tibi.</head>
               <l>FYe on thee <hi>Milo,</hi> how the poore abhorre thee,</l>
               <l>That ſtill wilt anſwer them, <hi>I haue not for thee:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When all thy kindred knowes, who thee condemne,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt it for thy Drabs, but not for them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Idem per huiuſmodi.</head>
               <l>A Nice young Dame that long'd for dainty Cates,</l>
               <l>With her that ſold them thus expoſtulates:</l>
               <l>My Noſe (I hope) ſhall be my Cooke (quoth ſhe)</l>
               <l>Mine Arſe (quoth th'other) may your Kitchin be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Aut caſte, aut caute.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>RAchell</hi> hath reaſon not to liue in Common,</l>
               <l>Thereby to ſhew her ſelfe a noted ſinner:</l>
               <l>But rather like a cloſe and ciuill woman,</l>
               <l>That to the Game ſeemes ſtill a young beginner:</l>
               <l>And not detected of her whoriſh life,</l>
               <l>May proue in time ſome honeſt Tradeſmans wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:16"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Oſcula qui ſumpſit, &amp;c.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>IAcke</hi> ſtill abiures it to his commen dation,</l>
               <l>Hee's yet a maide without equiuocation;</l>
               <l>That being woo'd by Wenches would reſiſt them,</l>
               <l>And neuer dealt with any but he kiſt them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Plus ſcaelera nocte.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>SIl.</hi> for his Wiues ſake much Tobacco ſells,</l>
               <l>That muſt aſſiſt him daily in his ſhop:</l>
               <l>And occupie her ſelfe in nothing elſe,</l>
               <l>But Pipes for Gentlemen to ſill and ſtop:</l>
               <l>Which ſhe neglects not whiles the day giues light,</l>
               <l>And burnes them as occaſion ſerues at night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Viuens, mortuus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MOunſeir Scuerus</hi> ſince his Office loſt,</l>
               <l>Wherein he liu'd of late a great Commander,</l>
               <l>Walks diſcontented like the angry Ghoſt</l>
               <l>Of proud <hi>Tarquinius,</hi> or <hi>Pope Alexander:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whom fates enuying, ſhould from vpſtart riſe,</l>
               <l>So puld him downe, as now he liuing dies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Et penna &amp; poculo.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>COlambus</hi> executes his Maſters place,</l>
               <l>Where he hath plodding beene twice ten yeeres ſpace:</l>
               <l>But ſimple howſoe'r the world may thinke him,</l>
               <l>Ther's not a Clarke mongſt twenty dares out drink him.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:16"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Patientia Vendicta.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cullus</hi> euermore will carrie ſway</l>
               <l>Ouer his wife in ſtrangers company:</l>
               <l>And on her lips his loathed fingers lay,</l>
               <l>Which patient ſhe puts vp in policy:</l>
               <l>But with her ſelfe reſolu'd in ſecret vowes,</l>
               <l>To p y him next day ſoundly on the browes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Foenum, dum coelum cerenum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>TRocus</hi> in Tauernes twice a day muſt bowze it,</l>
               <l>And belch Tobacco on his Clients purſes:</l>
               <l>No matter <hi>Trocus,</hi> 'tis thy place allowes it,</l>
               <l>Though like the Foxe 'canſt not eſcape from curſes.</l>
               <l>Who euer ſaw that Clarke like thee deputed,</l>
               <l>But had his fingers with purloyne polluted?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Pulchrior infaelicior.</head>
               <l>FIne Miſtriſſe <hi>Fedra</hi> famouſly accounted,</l>
               <l>Minding for recreation take the ayre,</l>
               <l>went in her Coach through <hi>London</hi> brauely mounted,</l>
               <l>(For what ſhould <hi>Fedra</hi> of the Fates deſpayre?)</l>
               <l>Strange and admirde, which might amaze the hearer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>That her owne horſes muſt to Bridewell beare her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Secundae cogitationes meliores.</head>
               <l>A Pamphlet was of Prouerbs pend by <hi>Polton,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wherein he thought all ſorts included were:</l>
               <l>Vntill one told him, <hi>Bate w'an ace quoth Bolton:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Indeed (ſaid hee) that Prouerbe is not there.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:17"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Vt naſus, notus.</head>
               <l>OLde <hi>Publius Naſo</hi> hath compoz'd a Play,</l>
               <l>Of ſuch a plot, as few or none that view it</l>
               <l>But will auouch he writes not euery day,</l>
               <l>Nor as the times of late (I would you knew it)</l>
               <l>The beſt in London payes for his inuention,</l>
               <l>Knowne to be ſimply ſuch as needes no mention.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad Lectorem.</head>
               <l>REader, theſe Epigrams long ſince compos'd,</l>
               <l>Should here by my conſent haue beene diſclos'd:</l>
               <l>Much leſſe at latter Lammas com'd in print,</l>
               <l>Had not the <hi>Stationer</hi> or the Diuell beene in't.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Grauidae formidiores.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DArkas</hi> cannot endure to ſee a Cat,</l>
               <l>A breſt of Mutton, or a Pigs head gaping:</l>
               <l>A Beare, a Bull, a Weazle or a Rat,</l>
               <l>No, nor the skreeking noyſe of Kettles ſcraping:</l>
               <l>Yet could imbrace a naked <hi>Cariball,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And nere be mou'd or frighted once withall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Confeſſe, and be hang'd.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>TOm</hi> ſtretcht his necke for ſtealing of a Mare,</l>
               <l>And yet Ile proue he was not hang'd for ſtealing:</l>
               <l>For had he not beene taken vnaware,</l>
               <l>And ſo conuicted by his owne reuealing,</l>
               <l>He might haue ſcapt the Gallowes, gone his way,</l>
               <l>And ſtill remain'd a Thiefe vntill this day.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:17"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Fama Alimentum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DAcus</hi> could giue good words, what ere was due,</l>
               <l>Whereby his credit leſſe in queſtion grew,</l>
               <l>Till baſe-borne Tapſters, without feare or grace,</l>
               <l>Muſt call him Banckrout 'fore his neighbours face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Omnia venalia Romae.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CAcus</hi> at firſt durſt ſcarce kiſſe Miſtriſſe <hi>Anne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But could at laſt to giue conſent aſſaile her:</l>
               <l>Who more reſpecting's money then the man,</l>
               <l>Ask't (hauing pur'ſt it) <hi>Are you not a Taylor?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How? 'sfoot (quoth <hi>Cacus</hi>) then for coyne I ſee,</l>
               <l>Taylors with Gentlemen muſt equall bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Aliqui fructus maturiores.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FReta,</hi> the forward'ſt of ten thouſand Gyrles,</l>
               <l>Wiſh't ſhe had beene at foureteene made a Page:</l>
               <l>To haue attended vpon Lords and Earles,</l>
               <l>That vnder Knights had ſeru'd at younger age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Edificium latrocinium.</head>
               <l>A Tennant by his Leaſe being bound to build,</l>
               <l>Of Timber-loggs his Land-lord had beguil'd,</l>
               <l>Which he perceiuing, 'gins with threats diſcuſſe,</l>
               <l>The danger of the Law that vs'd him thus.</l>
               <l>Alas (quoth he) 'twas done for my reliefe,</l>
               <l>Beſides, you know Sir, <hi>Building is a thiefe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:18"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Nocte latent menda.</head>
               <l>MIſtriſſe <hi>Roxana</hi> by no meanes endures</l>
               <l>The Curtaines of her Bed or Window drawne;</l>
               <l>Which to her eyes (ſaith ſhe) much hurt procures,</l>
               <l>And therefore hides them with a vayle of Lawne.</l>
               <l>But if you needes will haue the truth reueal'd,</l>
               <l>Her Noſe that's ſunke of late muſt be conceal'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Stante te ſtabit vxor.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>LIppus</hi> the Banckrout hath a bounſing Wife,</l>
               <l>That would be chaſte, were he but halfe ſo wiſe:</l>
               <l>And yet the Buzzard, for auoyding ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Liues in a Lane obſcur'd from watchfull eyes.</l>
               <l>Tut, <hi>Lippus</hi> be content, and beare withall,</l>
               <l>For if thou canſt not ſtand, ſhe needes muſt fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Leuia perdit quò lucret maiora.</head>
               <l>AWager on a Knight, of late was tride,</l>
               <l>He ſhould not beare ten pounds from out Cheape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe ſome Citizen holpe with his hands,</l>
               <l>To whom already he was bound in bands.</l>
               <l>Which well the Knight perceiu'd, elſe nere had done it,</l>
               <l>So that he loſt his wager, and yet won it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Puduit ſua damnareferre.</head>
               <l>SVch ill ſucceſſe had <hi>Dick</hi> at Dice laſt night,</l>
               <l>As he was for ſt next day play leaſt in ſight:</l>
               <l>But if you loue him make thereof no ſpeeches,</l>
               <l>He loſt his Rapier, Cloake, and veluet Breeches.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:18"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Strenuis, videri ſatis.</head>
               <l>WHen boaſting <hi>Bembus</hi> challeng'd is to fight,</l>
               <l>He ſeemes at firſt a very Diuell in ſight:</l>
               <l>Till more aduizde, will not defile hands,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe you meete him vpon <hi>Callice</hi> ſands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Chara nimis amicitia.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MIlo</hi> thinks much I ſhould his loue inherit,</l>
               <l>Saying, it's more then my deſerts can merit:</l>
               <l>Indeed hee ſpeaks <hi>Probatum eſt</hi> vnto me,</l>
               <l>For t'is ſo great as t'would in time vndo me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>In lingua, Patrià.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PEtrus</hi> eſpying late a youth paſſe by,</l>
               <l>Richly appareld, whom he knew but poore:</l>
               <l>Began to cenſure with him doubtfully,</l>
               <l>Whether it were the ſame he ſaw before.</l>
               <l>Till hearing him, in's language lay the law,</l>
               <l>Was ſure t'was then the ſelf-ſame
<hi>Corniſh</hi>-daw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Saepius ſoluas ſi ſaltabis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PLanus</hi> his money payd would faine be quiet,</l>
               <l>That penſiue erſt grew then more vext with woe:</l>
               <l>As ſcarce it could permit him time to diet,</l>
               <l>For poſting bout each office too and fro.</l>
               <l>Who for'ſt to daunce attendance durſt not reſt,</l>
               <l>Vntill the PIPE hath plaide <hi>Quietus est.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:19"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Creſcit furore Impudentia.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>TOruus</hi> will yet againe exceptions take,</l>
               <l>And ſweares that by's drink heel not endure theſe Rimes:</l>
               <l>Fye <hi>Toruus,</hi> let not men for manners ſake,</l>
               <l>Be made acquainted with thy ſhamefull crimes.</l>
               <l>But thowlt alledge the Baſtard is not thine,</l>
               <l>I ſhould not keep't then, if the caſe were mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſu, ſi non Auditu.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PRudence,</hi> reproou'd for walking in
<hi>Moorefields,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Straight from her Apronftrings this reaſon yeelds:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Though Women more then Men are thence debard,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T'is reaſon ſome be ſeene, becauſe not heard.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Fumus inimica Formae.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MAdam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entoſa</hi> carefull of her health,</l>
               <l>In haſte poſt haſte the Countrey ayre deſires:</l>
               <l>Sweating ſheel not endure for <hi>Londons</hi> wealth,</l>
               <l>Another winter of theſe Sea-cole Fires.</l>
               <l>Whoſe noyſome fume worſt then the ſoulſt infection,</l>
               <l>Had almoſt ſpoyld her Ladyſhips complexion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Cliricus natura.</head>
               <l>OLde <hi>Triſtram</hi> thought it well and wiſely done,</l>
               <l>With an <hi>Exchequer</hi> man to place his Sonne:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Triſtram</hi> had therein of wit no ſparke,</l>
               <l>To ſpoyle ſo good a Clowne for ſuch a Clarke.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:19"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Multorum Pignora pondus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PIgnus</hi> the <hi>Broker</hi> pil'de vp hath his Hall,</l>
               <l>With pawnes of perſons <hi>Alphabeticall:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Kept as his priſoners, &amp; his owne doth deeme them,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Bankroutes, Beggars, Bawdes,</hi> and <hi>Drabbes</hi> redeeme them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Arbora per Fructus.</head>
               <l>FIne Miſtreſſe <hi>Phippes,</hi> a proper Friend of mine,</l>
               <l>Wore on her breſt a paper <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who by a Mad cap one day being met,</l>
               <l>Askt her, <hi>Faire Lady, Is this Houſe to Let?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Maguis mirabile.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>SAltus</hi> ſo many ſorts of Sutes would weare,</l>
               <l>As once a weeke, he muſt be new inueſted:</l>
               <l>Which made him proudly to the world appeare,</l>
               <l>(For nere was <hi>Saltus</hi> vntill now Arreſted.)</l>
               <l>Strange on a ſudden that a man of might,</l>
               <l>Should breechleſſe liue, obſcur'd from out of ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Alienis Fortunatus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PRodus</hi> the Scriuener many a pound hath ſpent,</l>
               <l>Vpon procurements by him caus'd been lent:</l>
               <l>But with <hi>Prouiſo,</hi> will hee firſt indent,</l>
               <l>You muſt <hi>in Praſto,</hi> giue him good content,</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:20"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Potens in poculis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>GEorge</hi> will auouch it vpon deepe foundation,</l>
               <l>That drinking ſtore of wine hath made him wiſer,</l>
               <l>And more expert in matters variation,</l>
               <l>As hee's become a kinde of wits demſer;</l>
               <l>How he may cheating gull his Friends with Oathes,</l>
               <l>And fetch his <hi>Taylor</hi> off for more new cloathes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nimis docuit Conſuetudo.</head>
               <l>OLde <hi>Fucòs</hi> Board is oft repleniſhed,</l>
               <l>But nought thereof muſt be diminiſhed:</l>
               <l>Vnles ſome worthles vpper diſh or twaine,</l>
               <l>The reſt for ſeruice ſtill againe remaine.</l>
               <l>His man that vs'de to bring them in for ſhow,</l>
               <l>Leauing a diſh vpon the bench below:</l>
               <l>Was by his Maiſter (much offended) blam'de,</l>
               <l>Which he as briefe with anſwer bluntly fram'de;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tath bene zo often broft avore this day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As now chad thoft it zelfe had knowne the way.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Par pari refert.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>TObie</hi> with's wife, at Ticktack often playes,</l>
               <l>Who much ore-ſeeing, takes her many wayes:</l>
               <l>And yet hee proues the greater ouerſeer,</l>
               <l>Shee could, but will not aske him, <hi>Why not heere?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Rogandum coactus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FEſſus</hi> deſires all ſutes of Law might ceaſe,</l>
               <l>For being Outlaw'd, faine would liue in peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:20"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Sere Poenitentia ſeue.</head>
               <l>A Seriant that fell ſicke tooke late remorce,</l>
               <l>On many Priſoners hee had plagu'd by force:</l>
               <l>And now would free them from the <hi>Counter</hi>-hole,</l>
               <l>But that <hi>Toe late;</hi> thinks t'will not helpe his ſoule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Non Morbus, ſed Dolor.</head>
               <l>A Doctor tolde his Patient <hi>Omphida,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The paine ſhee felt was a <hi>Scyatica:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which ſhe not perfect how to nominat,</l>
               <l>Miſtaking; Cryes: <hi>Oh my Certificat!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nullum ſtimulum Ignauis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CAecus</hi> awak't, was tolde the Sunne appeard,</l>
               <l>Which had the darknes of the morning cleard:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Caecus</hi> ſluggiſh thereto makes replie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Sunne hath further farre to goe then I.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad Momum.</head>
               <l>CEaſe prethee <hi>Momus,</hi> bite thy malice in,</l>
               <l>Tut man, I knowe thou haſt a diuelliſh wit:</l>
               <l>Able to poze the wiſeſt of thy kin,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Momus</hi> then thou ſhould'ſt not boaſt of it.</l>
               <l>Or ſay, thou worke the worſt thou canſt intend,</l>
               <l>That done, goe hang thy ſelfe, and ther's an end.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:21"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Humilis Sublimis.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>KAte,</hi> ſeeming curious in her conuerſation,</l>
               <l>Scorns you ſhould kiſſe her hand or tye her ſhoo:</l>
               <l>Which ſhee accounts as great an imputation,</l>
               <l>As any worſt of wrong you elſe can doo.</l>
               <l>So high ſhee vaunts her ſelfe aboue the Skyes,</l>
               <l>And yet full lowly on a Straw-bed lyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Seruus dominatur Domino.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſan</hi> hath ſeru'd this yeare and halfe for nought,</l>
               <l>Making ſtill good, things broken, ſtolne, or loſt:</l>
               <l>Which with her wages muſt anew be bought,</l>
               <l>That doe amount vnto no little coſt.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Suſan</hi> now hath found a meanes for all,</l>
               <l>What time her Miſtreſſe goes abroad <hi>(olde Trot)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To yeeld herſelfe vnto her Maſters call,</l>
               <l>And make him Father what another got.</l>
               <l>Who rather choſe, then Law the <hi>Caſe</hi> ſhould handle,</l>
               <l>To pay a hundrd pounds for ſope and candle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Tandem aperta Reeluſa.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>BEttrice</hi> debard from ſport, with one that lou'd her,</l>
               <l>Was kept ſeuerely vnder bolt and locke:</l>
               <l>Who notwithſtanding when occaſion mou'd her,</l>
               <l>Crept forth at th'window, nightly in her ſmocke.</l>
               <l>But from her Father fortie weekes conceald it,</l>
               <l>Vntill the <hi>Bastard</hi> cride, and ſo reueald it.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:21"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Suauiora Digniora.</head>
               <l>YOung Miſtreſſe <hi>Minea</hi> findes her ſelfe agrieued,</l>
               <l>In that her Husband keepes her not in faſhion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And therefore will by others be relieued,</l>
               <l>Who on ſuch creatures take farre more compaſſion.</l>
               <l>No fleſh ſhee feares to feede on out of ſight,</l>
               <l>Knowing her good-man picks the bones at night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enditur vt Emitur.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DArcas</hi> will doo with Knight or Gentleman</l>
               <l>What ſhall be reaſon, more then which ſhee dares not:</l>
               <l>And that's as much as any woman can,</l>
               <l>Vnles be ſuch as for her credit cares not.</l>
               <l>Then if theſe pleaſures without feare enſue,</l>
               <l>What thereto longs (qd. <hi>Darcas</hi>) pray iudge you?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Meritrix abſentè Marito.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſan</hi> with ſundry cunning ſlights and trickes,</l>
               <l>Gulls her Good-man that dominering ſwaies:</l>
               <l>Nor will her eyes other obiects fixe,</l>
               <l>Whiles in her companie the <hi>Cockscomb</hi> ſtaies.</l>
               <l>Who gone, ſhee cannot for her life refraine,</l>
               <l>But needs muſt laugh, till downe ſhee falls againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nocte latent mende.</head>
               <l>WHen bounſing <hi>Bettrice</hi> minded is to ſport,</l>
               <l>She cloſely ſteales out of her dores at night:</l>
               <l>And couets moſt mongſt ſtrangers to reſort,</l>
               <l>That leaſt may be diſcernd by Candle-light.</l>
               <l>For chiefe reſpects which might her much diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Beſides her <hi>Perriwigge,</hi> and pocky face.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:22"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad Iohannem Bradſhaw, Seaccarienſem.</head>
               <l>NOt that to mee thou ere wert Friend or Foe,</l>
               <l>Nor that I ſeeke heereby t'inſinuate:</l>
               <l>Nor that thou wouldſt the world thy worth ſhuld know,</l>
               <l>Which Ile not blaze, nor yet expoſtulate.</l>
               <l>Onely repute thee one amongſt thoſe Clarks,</l>
               <l>Gainſt whom my <hi>Maſtiue</hi> neyther bytes nor barks.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>In Obitum alicuius.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lampus</hi> extinct at laſt in <hi>Aſhes</hi> lyes,</l>
               <l>Who when hee liu'd did nought but Gormandize:</l>
               <l>On choyceſt cheere, and Bolles fill'd to the brim,</l>
               <l>Which fedde him fatte, for worms that feede on him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Plus decus Honori.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PIerce</hi> grown to yeares, maintain's a Page at's heeles</l>
               <l>That muſt attend, and tell him what's a clocke:</l>
               <l>When hee from <hi>Trulls &amp; Tauernes</hi> homeward reeles,</l>
               <l>And in ſhort time conſum'd and ſpent his ſtocke.</l>
               <l>Yet biddes prouide gainſt night ſome other toye,</l>
               <l>Whiles belching hee repoſe his head that's giddie;</l>
               <l>Then waking calls, <hi>Fill ſome Tobacco Boye:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That done, Goe ſee if Supper be made readie.</l>
               <l>Which hee not hauing wherewith to diſcharge,</l>
               <l>(Nor daring futher runne vpon the ſcore:)</l>
               <l>Intreats the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>intner</hi> with diſcourſe at large,</l>
               <l>Vpon his Cloake to lend him ſo much more.</l>
               <l>Nor meanes hee thence till midnight part away,</l>
               <l>And keepe his bedde vntill next Quarter day.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:22"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Efficit prostrata, nummus.</head>
               <l>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Iaques</hi> from th'Exchange goes home to ſup,</l>
               <l>And findes his Wife drunke on her pillow laid:</l>
               <l>He patiently prepar'd to put it vp,</l>
               <l>Encounters with blacke <hi>Kate</hi> his Kitchin maid:</l>
               <l>Who tells him, ſhee'll no longer ſerue his turne,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe his Maſter-ſhip more crownes disburſe,</l>
               <l>And therefore bids him make her not forſworne,</l>
               <l>But preſently diſpatch and draw his purſe:</l>
               <l>Which done, ſhe flatly to her buſineſſe falles,</l>
               <l>And nere ariſeth till her Miſtriſſe calles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Subita, magis quaerenda.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MAt.</hi> with his Man late ſet on meriment,</l>
               <l>And therewith trying by ſome tricke to flout him:</l>
               <l>Spying his Dogge that to ſir-reuerence went,</l>
               <l>Ask't if he had not Pen and Inke about him.</l>
               <l>Yes, ſaid his man (and wherefore makes he doubt?)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To write</hi> (quoth's Maſter) <hi>what my Dogge layes out.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Pecunia, virum.</head>
               <l>A <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer</hi> waxt worth ten thouſand pound,</l>
               <l>Which with extortion he had gayn'd of late:</l>
               <l>For purchaſe ſhould of certaine Lands be bound</l>
               <l>Vnto a Knight that knew not his eſtate:</l>
               <l>But to a Scriuener dwelling neere him goes,</l>
               <l>And for aduiſe therein his counſell takes,</l>
               <l>Knowing he could the truth thereof diſcloſe:</l>
               <l>Who whiſpring in his eare, this anſwere makes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You neede not Sir, the matter further ſcan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Ile aſſure you hee's a right good man.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:23"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Plus mendax, Mendicus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>DAcus</hi> giues out for payment of his debts,</l>
               <l>He ſhall a wondrous wealthy Widdow wed:</l>
               <l>Which 'mongſt his Creditors much hope begets,</l>
               <l>That conſtant are 'twill be accompliſhed.</l>
               <l>Meane while young <hi>Dacus</hi> takes vp ten times more,</l>
               <l>Tells them the mariage day is ſhort at hand,</l>
               <l>When hee'll no leſſe then double all reſtore,</l>
               <l>Which neede no queſtion now of Bill or Band.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Dacus</hi> makes it a more gulling toy,</l>
               <l>Then that old Coſenage of new Englands-ioy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Detur laus digniori.</head>
               <l>MIſtriſſe <hi>Marina</hi> 'mongſt ſome Goſſips ſat,</l>
               <l>Where Faces were the ſubiect of their chat:</l>
               <l>Some lok't too pale, ſome ſeem'd too firie red,</l>
               <l>Some browne, ſome blacke, and ſome ill faſhioned.</l>
               <l>Good Lord (quoth ſhe) you all are much too blame,</l>
               <l>Let's loue and prayſe the Maker of the ſame.</l>
               <l>Her Chamber-mayd who heard her, ſtanding by,</l>
               <l>Said, <hi>Then loue me, for that you know was I.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Nil perdunt mendici.</head>
               <l>I <hi>Ack's</hi> wondrous ſicke, who thinks hee ſhall goe mad,</l>
               <l>And loſe his wits (a thing <hi>Iacke</hi> neuer had:)</l>
               <l>Take comfort man, if that be all thou feareſt,</l>
               <l>A groat will pay thy loſſe when witts are deareſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:23"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Formoſa foetida.</head>
               <l>I Met with <hi>Martha,</hi> and fayn'd would haue kiſt her,</l>
               <l>who turn'd her cheeke, which made me that I miſt her:</l>
               <l>She ſpar'd her lipps, becauſe her breath was tainted,</l>
               <l>And I her cheekes, becauſe I fain'd them painted.</l>
               <l>Since then at firſt, we had no better greeting,</l>
               <l>Your hand (quoth I) ſhall ſerue at our next meeting.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Materia pro forma.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cina</hi> hath a Loue whoſe name is
<hi>Gooſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A propper Lad, well borne, and wondrous ſpruee:</l>
               <l>She likes the man, but cannot brooke his name,</l>
               <l>If that be all (ſweete <hi>Luce</hi>) you are too blame.</l>
               <l>The man you may commit into your hands.</l>
               <l>For why, the Babes he gets may prooue all Swans,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Sero, ſi non ſubito.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>LOrellus</hi> by the Law condemn'd to dye,</l>
               <l>Sent his ſicke water to a Doctor nigh:</l>
               <l>And proffer'd him an hundred pound for's paine,</l>
               <l>If by his Art hee might but's life obtaine.</l>
               <l>The Doctor vnderſtanding of his crime,</l>
               <l>Wil'd him with patience to endure a time;</l>
               <l>And fend againe when th' Moone was in the change,</l>
               <l>Meane while <hi>Lorelius</hi> muſt to Tiburne range.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:24"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Tria, vertit in vnum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FEſtinus</hi> now in haſt reſolues to thriue,</l>
               <l>Ere Chriſtmas next, and honeſtly will wiue:</l>
               <l>Sweares by his locks hee'll ramble then no more,</l>
               <l>But keepe him cloſe to's wife, and's friend, not's whore.</l>
               <l>Inſooth <hi>Feſtinus,</hi> 'twere diſcreetly done,</l>
               <l>For hauing charge, to haue all three in one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Secretaſua ſibi.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>LEttice</hi> hath left the towne: but who knowes why?</l>
               <l>Some ſay to take the ayre, and ſee a friend:</l>
               <l>I heard as much; but knew it was a lye,</l>
               <l>Her buſineſſe tended to another end.</l>
               <l>No Doctor heere can cure her, ſhee's ſo ill,</l>
               <l>Old Mother-Midwife hath therein more skill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Pluma, quid leuius?</head>
               <l>WHat if <hi>Pondexus</hi> Wife be light? how then?</l>
               <l>Muſt ſhe be taunted at by euery Iade?</l>
               <l>This is the fault of fooliſh vaine women,</l>
               <l>That will be diuing in their neighbours trade.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pon:</hi> is a Feather-maker, and by right</l>
               <l>His Wife, like to her Wares may prooue as light.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:24"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad Samuelem.</head>
               <l>MY ſute's to you <hi>(Sam)</hi> 'pray deny it not:</l>
               <l>If you remember't, you a Bracelet got</l>
               <l>From your ſweete Miſtriſſe; 'faith reſtor't againe,</l>
               <l>Twill doe her pleaſure now: for to be plaine,</l>
               <l>She hath ſo great a loſſe had in that kinde,</l>
               <l>As in the world ſhe knowes not where to finde</l>
               <l>One ſilly hayre of her owne ſimple breede;</l>
               <l>Then helpe her now, that holpe you at your neede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>A malo ad peius.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PRiſcus</hi> though nere ſo poore, yet herein ioyes,</l>
               <l>He once was Captaine of the Roaring-boyes:</l>
               <l>And worthy then durſt challenge as his due,</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt place amongſt thoſe damned crew,</l>
               <l>That with vnbutning could carouſe a quart,</l>
               <l>Drinke drunke, and ſober, ſixe times ere he part:</l>
               <l>Knocke at cach Gate at midnight on command,</l>
               <l>And make the Porter ſtand with cap in hand,</l>
               <l>Suppoſing him a man of that regard,</l>
               <l>As ſcornes to paſſe not giuing good reward.</l>
               <l>When he (poore Raſcall) but a rambling goes,</l>
               <l>And now in Limbo lowzy lies, God knowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Dubitat mens conſcia recti.</head>
               <l>WHy ſhould Sir <hi>Pandrus</hi> ſo impatient be,</l>
               <l>As needes hee'll call in queſtion who I am:</l>
               <l>That durſt preſume on ſuch a one as he,</l>
               <l>To write a Satyre or an Epigram.</l>
               <l>Let me Sir <hi>Pandrus,</hi> tell you this for true,</l>
               <l>I am not ſuch a ſlandrous knaue as you imagin.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:25"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Nemo odit quod neſcit.</head>
               <l>YOung <hi>Fawnus</hi> ſpends thrice fortie pounds a yeare,</l>
               <l>True Demonſtration that hee'l nere be thriftie:</l>
               <l>But what need <hi>Fawnus</hi> Fates or Fortunes feare,</l>
               <l>Thats yet not fourteene, and his <hi>Dad</hi> paſt fiftie.</l>
               <l>Who ſimply pard'ning any worſt of merit,</l>
               <l>Will nere his firſt borne <hi>Baſtard</hi> diſinherit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Sine Flamma combuſtus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MArcus</hi> came vp to ſee the <hi>Monuments,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Tower,</hi> the <hi>Lyons,</hi> and the new
<hi>Exchange:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Water-works,</hi> and lofty <hi>London</hi>-Rents,</l>
               <l>With other ſights, that ſeem'd to <hi>Marcus</hi> ſtrange.</l>
               <l>But mongſt the reſt that likewiſe did abound,</l>
               <l>Nere thought on <hi>Fyre-works,</hi> which he firſt here found</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ritur Impertunitate.</head>
               <l>A Luſtie Laſſe, but looſe, not worth the naming,</l>
               <l>went down the ſtaires wheron ſhe feard to ſtumble</l>
               <l>And holding in her hand a Candle flaming,</l>
               <l>Was by a iolly Lad intic'de to iumble.</l>
               <l>Who when at firſt he gan her roughly handle,</l>
               <l>Away ſhee cride: Now fie how you abuſe mee:</l>
               <l>And therewith vowing, ſwore: Now by this Candle,</l>
               <l>Ile burne you Sir (if thus you ſtriue to vſe mee.</l>
               <l>Hee blew the Candle out, to breake her vow,</l>
               <l>But ſhee performd her Oath; imagine how.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:25"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Facilis Generoſus.</head>
               <l>WHo ſayes <hi>Humfridus</hi> is not gentle borne?</l>
               <l>Did not <hi>Crispinus</hi> beat him th'other morne?</l>
               <l>And hee it gently tooke, without reſiſting?</l>
               <l>Then let him paſſe, and leaue your further ieſting.</l>
               <l>Hee that for blowes hath halfe ſo good diſgeſtion,</l>
               <l>Muſt needes proue Gentleman without all queſtion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Dulee Bellum inexpertis.</head>
               <l>MOunſieur <hi>Securus,</hi> prowde as any hee,</l>
               <l>Pray's ſtill for Warre and braue Hoſtilitie:</l>
               <l>But hee's no better then a barking Dogge,</l>
               <l>Or rather as a painted skipping Frogge,</l>
               <l>That bragges it out with borrowed brauerie,</l>
               <l>Warre is no colour for ſuch knauerie.</l>
               <l>How can he thinke to hurt his Enemie,</l>
               <l>When all his Weapons are at Surgerie?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>In Amoroſum.</head>
               <l>HAd I not vow'd almoſt to write no more,</l>
               <l>Spruce <hi>(Amoroſus)</hi> I could not forbeare:</l>
               <l>To tell the world how like a common-Whore,</l>
               <l>Thou ſpend'ſt each morne in trimming of thy haire.</l>
               <l>Which hauing done, and finiſht nere ſo ſoone,</l>
               <l>Thou look'ſt no better then a wilde <hi>Baboone.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:26"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Perplunias Anſer.</head>
               <l>SEe how young <hi>Rufus</hi> walkes in greene each day,</l>
               <l>As if he nere was youthfull vntill now:</l>
               <l>Ere Chriſtmas next this greene-Gooſe will be gray,</l>
               <l>And thoſe high burniſht Plumes in's Cap will bow.</l>
               <l>But yet you wrong him, ſince his purſe is full,</l>
               <l>To call him Gooſe, that is ſo young a Gull.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad Momum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>MOmus,</hi> you told me late I did not well,</l>
               <l>Seeming as 'twere my little wit to ſell:</l>
               <l>Why man, the Aegyptians ſold their babes for gaine,</l>
               <l>And may not I the Infant of my braine?</l>
               <l>But well I wot thou'lt ſet it ſoone at naught,</l>
               <l>And ſay the Childe is better fed then taught.</l>
               <l>Peace <hi>Momus,</hi> peace, either thy good word lend it,</l>
               <l>Or come and take my roome till thou canſt mend it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Et Puella, &amp; Foemina.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cina's</hi> yeeres runnes on ſo ſmooth and euen,</l>
               <l>That at ſixteene ſhee ſeeemes but as eleuen:</l>
               <l>Yet marke how ſtrange the time had her beguilde,</l>
               <l>Who prou'd a Mother being but a Childe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:26"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Omnibus hoc <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itium.</head>
               <l>AN honeſt Conſtable that made ſearch of late,</l>
               <l>And found a fellow with a wench in Bed:</l>
               <l>Wiſh't hee himſelfe had bene Aſſociate,</l>
               <l>And therefore kindely bad them both God ſpeed.</l>
               <l>Be ſure (qd, he) Ile not deſcrie your lurking,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Nature</hi> (that's ſo well prouok't) be working.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Prodit ſe lingua.</head>
               <l>A Countrey Butcher late with Oxen paſſes,</l>
               <l>Hard by a Dame that kept a ſhop of glaſſes:</l>
               <l>Who liſping chides him with words finicall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thirra</hi> remoue your <hi>Ballocks</hi> from my Stall.</l>
               <l>Whereat the <hi>Butcher</hi> ſmiling makes a ſtop,</l>
               <l>But ſhe with anger, bluſhing leaues her ſhop.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Admonita peior.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PRiſcill</hi> doth plainely to the world appeale,</l>
               <l>Since Women that deale plaine, are Baladiz'd:</l>
               <l>Shee'l with her Husband no more plainely deale,</l>
               <l>Or mongſt plaine dealing people be compriz'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Dum friget, caleſcit.</head>
               <l>WHo doubts but <hi>Suſun</hi> when ſhe firſt bore ſway,</l>
               <l>Had for one night a <hi>French Crown</hi> pitch &amp; pay;</l>
               <l>But who ſo ſimple now, knowes not the reaſon</l>
               <l>Shee tooke not Dyet, nor the Sweate in ſeaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:27"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Aſinus ex Aſino.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>GRillus</hi> outragious grewe with ſelfe conceit,</l>
               <l>Dreaming of late hee was transformd an Aſſe:</l>
               <l>And waking, needes would to the world repeat,</l>
               <l>That it for certaine truth came ſo to paſſe.</l>
               <l>Who thus beſotted, forthwith gins to bray,</l>
               <l>Attempteth eke like <hi>Bankes his Horſe</hi> to daunce,</l>
               <l>Runnes to the Stable there to feede on Hay,</l>
               <l>Striues to Coruet, Cariere, Kick, Wince and praunce,</l>
               <l>But ſince that <hi>Grillus,</hi> nothing ſo much feares,</l>
               <l>As the appearance of his <hi>Aſſes</hi> eares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Non dulce, quod vtile.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rdoſus</hi> train de in the <hi>Nocturnall</hi> Trade,</l>
               <l>Which wee by Title of <hi>Gold-finder</hi> call:</l>
               <l>With oft infuſion ſuch eſcapes had made,</l>
               <l>As cauſd his Maiſter (much diſpleaſd withall)</l>
               <l>Say thus in rage <hi>Thou a Iakes-Farmer</hi> proue?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Cobler</hi> (knaue) would thee much more behoue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To my Booke-ſeller.</head>
               <l>THy Bookes (I doubt not) but will all be bought,</l>
               <l>Though nere ſo bitter for the <hi>Title</hi> thought:</l>
               <l>To putrifactious <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> that abide,</l>
               <l>The ſtrongeſt Medicines muſt bee applide.</l>
               <l>Yet may be well inough indur'd: all which,</l>
               <l>Are but as Worme-wood giuen to kill the itch.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:27"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Nnda <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritas.</head>
               <l>YOung Miſtreſſe <hi>Siſley,</hi> and her Siſter
<hi>Kate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Scornes to be thought with tricks t'equiuocate:</l>
               <l>Therfore ſayes plaine, if twere not true they ſwore,</l>
               <l>Let each be cenſurd for an arrant Whore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Soluat vtcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Senex.</head>
               <l>OLd <hi>Squinto</hi> deales with's Wench not like a ſtranger</l>
               <l>Though comes perhaps but once a Weeke, or ſo:</l>
               <l>T'is knowne he keeps her ſtill at Rack and manger</l>
               <l>Whether ſhee loue or loath him yea, or no.</l>
               <l>He payes for all ſhe ſpends, and eates, or drinkes:</l>
               <l>Allowes her Horſe and Coath to ryde at pleaſure,</l>
               <l>Yea what ſhee beſt for recreation thinkes,</l>
               <l>That bids her vſe, and chuſe againe at pleaſure.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus doth the Dotard</hi> dull and deteſtable,</l>
               <l>Make others doe what hee himſelfe's not able.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Sperare liceat Infidelibus.</head>
               <l>THat <hi>Luſcus</hi> hath no <hi>Lattin</hi> t'is no Lye,</l>
               <l>Nor that hee writeth falſe <hi>Ortographye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet paſſeth for a <hi>Checquer Clearke</hi> we ſee,</l>
               <l>And hopes this Tearme to purchaſe many a Fee.</l>
               <l>Nay more he hopes to proue an Officer,</l>
               <l>If caſe (quoth hee) our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar</hi> doth not erre:</l>
               <l>Who well remembers in his <hi>Prouerbs</hi> ſaith,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The weake in Knowledge, may be ſtrong in Faith.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:28"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Caſta, quam nomo rogauit.</head>
               <l>VVHy tempt you me (qd. <hi>Win</hi>) with words vnchaſt?</l>
               <l>Or doe you loue to ſpend your breath in waſt?</l>
               <l>I am not Syr, the Wench you take me for,</l>
               <l>But ſcorne the motion, and your words abhorre.</l>
               <l>T'is knowne how well I liue without diſgrace,</l>
               <l>And therefore choſen haue this priuate place.</l>
               <l>Where, ſince the time we may not long inherit,</l>
               <l>Your Welcome muſt be therefore as you merit.</l>
               <l>Alas (good Syr) you are to mee a ſtranger,</l>
               <l>But that's all one, when you are free from daunger</l>
               <l>I am perſwaded (though your yeares be young)</l>
               <l>You haue a ſubtil and inticing toung,</l>
               <l>Able to tempt a Woman goe aſtray,</l>
               <l>Should ſhee not haue the grace to ſay you may.</l>
               <l>Fye, who would truſt theſe men vpon their words?</l>
               <l>The world mongſt twenty ſcarce one true affoords.</l>
               <l>But to giue each his due, I muſt confeſſe,</l>
               <l>You nere as yet haue wrongd me more or leſſe.</l>
               <l>Nay, pray for beare, my Maide heares all your wooings,</l>
               <l>Shee knowes I am not vſde vnto ſuch dooings.</l>
               <l>You talke of matters worth as much as nought,</l>
               <l>But not a word what Money you haue brought.</l>
               <l>Nor euer dreame you at what charge wee liue,</l>
               <l>That for our Lodgings thus much weekly giue.</l>
               <l>Which ſuch as you (alas) nere thinke vpon,</l>
               <l>That once haue had your pleaſures, and are gone.</l>
               <l>What, will you Syr diſpatch and make an ende?</l>
               <l>Come: you ſhall ſee Ile vſe you as a Frende,</l>
               <l>And as befits a man of your eſtate,</l>
               <l>Nor loue I many words expoſtulate.</l>
               <l>Belieue Syr, as you are a Gentleman,</l>
               <l>I tooke no handfell ſince the Terme began.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:28"/>
               <l>Then in a manner thinke your ſelfe ſo ſpedde,</l>
               <l>As purchaſe may my ſecond May denhed.</l>
               <l>Which though I ſay't, and doe not vſe to flout,</l>
               <l>Good Knights haue ſude for oft, and gone without:</l>
               <l>Whats there? Two ſhillings ſix pence? mary muſſe:</l>
               <l>You thinke belike wee are ſome common ſtuffe:</l>
               <l>Yes, in good time, t'were more then fitte I graunt yee,</l>
               <l>You need but aske and haue, yes Syr <hi>I waunt yee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I thought as much how franck you were before,</l>
               <l>Dee vſe to giue your <hi>Hackney</hi>-Iades no more?</l>
               <l>Twer good you kept it ſtill Syr and were going,</l>
               <l>Aſſure your ſelfe I am not for your mowing,</l>
               <l>Nor any mans that me ſo baſely ſcan,</l>
               <l>My Maide gets ſo much of each Seruing-man.</l>
               <l>Make you no difference pray twixt her and mee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Or muſt wee both alike reputed bee;</l>
               <l>Well Sir is that the mayne you will disburſe?</l>
               <l>Or haue you no more Money in your purſe?</l>
               <l>The time I ſpend about this idle chat,</l>
               <l>May looſe and hinder mee I know not what.</l>
               <l>Piſh; yet more dooing? pray Syr hold your hand,</l>
               <l>And ieſt with thoſe you boldly may command.</l>
               <l>Had I not thought you one of better proofe,</l>
               <l>You nere ſhould entred haue within my roofe.</l>
               <l>A man of your ſort, ſparing his expence?</l>
               <l>I pray Syr hold me not I muſt goe hence.</l>
               <l>But ere I part, knowe without more relate,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A French Crowne</hi> is my leaſt and loweſt rate.</l>
               <l>Which if you haue not, you may leaue ſome pawne,</l>
               <l>Nor will I to a dodkin leſſe be drawne.</l>
               <l>But ſcorne for thrice as much I tell you true,</l>
               <l>Thus proſtitute my ſelfe, wert not to you.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tut,</hi> nere tell me youl come againe and pay,</l>
               <l>I haue too oft bene vs de with ſuch delay.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:29"/>
               <l>Nor talke of Oaths as promiſe once gone hence,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wee loue the Preſent, not the Future Tence.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You know my minde: the'res now no more to ſay;</l>
               <l>Doe this, or here's the Dore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ther's the way.</l>
               <l>—<hi>Cetera deficiunt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Mens conſcia recti.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>RAlph</hi> told his Miſtreſſe hee had done with her,</l>
               <l>Which ſhe conceiu'd at worſt and calld him knaue</l>
               <l>Threatning to bring him 'fore an Officer</l>
               <l>Where ſhee th'advantage of the Law might haue.</l>
               <l>Indeed (qd. <hi>Ralph</hi>) I nere preſumd ſo on you,</l>
               <l>Till now you pleaſd' to take the <hi>Whore</hi> vpon you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Hypocrita videatur.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>llus</hi> ſuppoſeth none obſerues his haunts,</l>
               <l>Of ſtealing ſecretly vnto mine <hi>Aunts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Without his <hi>Page;</hi> Oh Syr it might be ſaid,</l>
               <l>He elſe were ſeene to kiſſe the
<hi>Kitchin-Mayde.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or ſuffer <hi>Siſſe</hi> or <hi>Suſan</hi> ſearch his Hoſe,</l>
               <l>Which to the world his <hi>Page</hi> might chance diſcloſe.</l>
               <l>Tut <hi>Pullus</hi> can ſuch after-claps remoue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et ſi non castè, tamen cautè</hi> proue.</l>
               <l>For nere of him was yet more ſeene or hard,</l>
               <l>Then of blinde <hi>George,</hi> or <hi>Iohn</hi> of
<hi>Pauls-Church-yarde.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Meliùs ſit per Deputatum.</head>
               <l>A Clyent that to <hi>London</hi> came for Law,</l>
               <l>In right of Land which ſome had ſought withdraw</l>
               <l>Finding his <hi>Aduocate</hi> gone forth a mile,</l>
               <l>Propounds the <hi>Caſe</hi> vnto his wife the while.</l>
               <l>Who ſoone deciding it without expence,</l>
               <l>Tolde him the fault was in his Euidence.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:29"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Cedendum neceſſitati.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>FRauciſcas</hi> ſweares hee'l be no more forſworne,</l>
               <l>No more will Swagger, Surfet, or be drunck:</l>
               <l>No more his locks will weare at length but ſhorne,</l>
               <l>No more converſe or ſollace with his Punck.</l>
               <l>No more chaſt Widdowes, Maides, or Wiues abuſe,</l>
               <l>No more leawd Songs, or bawdy termes repeat:</l>
               <l>No more <hi>Tobacco</hi> midſt of Dinners vſe;</l>
               <l>No more detract, lye, flatter, cogge, or cheat.</l>
               <l>For true it is, <hi>Time</hi> now hath better taught him,</l>
               <l>Since late that ſcuruy <hi>Woodſtreet-Counter</hi> caught him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Neſcit Stultus iraſci.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>COdrus</hi> a Countrey Clowne, well worth the naming</l>
               <l>Fell amongſt Gameſters late to learne their vice:</l>
               <l>That (ſoone intreated,) drawne was into Gaming,</l>
               <l>And gulld of all his Golde, with cheating Dice;</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Codrus</hi> ſeeing, halfe in anger ſwore,</l>
               <l>They nere from him ſhould gaine one penny more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuitur ex Fumo.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſcus</hi> growes fat, yet feedes on nought at all,</l>
               <l>How liues hee then to any Creatures thincking?</l>
               <l>Oh Syr, by precepts Metaphyſicall,</l>
               <l>For know that <hi>Fuſcus</hi> deales in nought but drinking,</l>
               <l>No foode at all his Fancie can prouoke,</l>
               <l>But wholeſome liquor, and a Pipe of Smoke.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:30"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad Conſcium, Epilogus.</head>
               <l>NOw what ſayes <hi>Conſcius</hi> to theſe ſcuruy Rymes,</l>
               <l>Are they not baſeſt moſt abſurd abuſes?</l>
               <l>Hadſt not bene better by a thouſand times,</l>
               <l>T'haue ſpent thy ſixe-pence vpon other vſes?</l>
               <l>Come, th'art an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> nor canſt by Approbation,</l>
               <l>Say yet preciſely where the Saddle wrings:</l>
               <l>Onely doeſt feele by natures inclination,</l>
               <l>The more a Horſe is galld, the more hee flings.</l>
               <l>Harke in thine Eare, if this thou thinkſt diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Next time Ile ride thee through the Market-place.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="satires">
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:30"/>
            <head>SATYRS.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Magnis, peccata mìnus.</head>
               <l>YEe nimble <hi>Satyrs,</hi> that with howling ſtraine,</l>
               <l>Belch out the poyſoned' Canker yee containe</l>
               <l>Of Earths pollution, and the worlds offence,</l>
               <l>Maskt and obſcur'd with ſecret vile pretence;</l>
               <l>You that delight to torture men aliue,</l>
               <l>And through the channels of deſtruction diue;</l>
               <l>Avaunt, diſpatch, and looke yee not protract,</l>
               <l>To bring to light, each hainous horrid act.</l>
               <l>What? Stand yee fearfull of mens outward features?</l>
               <l>Or dread ye ſhadowes but of painted Creatures</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſeeming outſides onely made for ſhowe</l>
               <l>Aſſume the ſubſtance which themſelues not know;</l>
               <l>Or is't becauſe you ſcorne to dignifie</l>
               <l>The leawde ambition of prowd baſtardie;</l>
               <l>Where can yee finde within Earths continent,</l>
               <l>Men of that rare refined Element</l>
               <l>Who fearing to be damnd or checkt for blame,</l>
               <l>Are more leſſe ſubiect vnto ſinne then ſhame;</l>
               <l>But ſo delight in lewdnes to excell,</l>
               <l>As they prooue Diuells before they come to Hell;</l>
               <l>Drunck with the dregges of ſinnne inſatiate,</l>
               <l>Appearing Monſters moſt adulterate.</l>
               <l>Careleſſe of Bliſſe, of Conſcience, or of Soule,</l>
               <l>Till glut of guiltines their deedes controule:</l>
               <l>And they with Vleers ſo infected are,</l>
               <l>As euery limme is blemiſht with a skarre</l>
               <l>Of ſhameleſſe, leawde, and loath'd iniquitie,</l>
               <l>Sprung from the loynes of luſt and infamie.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:31"/>
               <l>Nurſt with the milke of that infectious euill,</l>
               <l>Which thus hath made them Chiildren for the Diuell.</l>
               <l>And now ſwolln bigge with bluſhleſſe Impudence,</l>
               <l>Preſume their greatnes may with <hi>Ioue</hi> diſpence.</l>
               <l>preſcribing to themſelues thoſe rules of reaſons,</l>
               <l>As muſt accord with their owne times and ſeaſons.</l>
               <l>What's hee that's drunck, or ſurſets (hauing wealth)</l>
               <l>But will alledge t'is Phyſicke for his health.</l>
               <l>That <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> ſports and Carnall appetite</l>
               <l>Are for euacuation requiſite.</l>
               <l>That murder rape and inceſt (threatning ruth)</l>
               <l>Are all but held as idle toyes of Youth.</l>
               <l>Miſchiefes that pleaſures bring who would preuent,</l>
               <l>Ther's tyme (ſay they) hereafter to repent.</l>
               <l>Or that their beſt of deedes are done too late,</l>
               <l>If to be damnd it be predeſtinate.</l>
               <l>Some Woolues in Sheep-Skinnes wrapt gainſt ſuch men barke,</l>
               <l>And care not what themſelues doe in the darke.</l>
               <l>Yet chiefly are or daind to rule the rout,</l>
               <l>Becauſe their Office herein beares them out.</l>
               <l>Who knowes not Greatnes may diſpence with Lawes,</l>
               <l>Thers no reſiſtance in a rich mans cauſe.</l>
               <l>For thoſe bewitching Obiects, Golde and pleaſure,</l>
               <l>Are <hi>Plutoes</hi> Agents that augments his treaſure.</l>
               <l>And do perſwade vs, there's no Hell but feare,</l>
               <l>No life, nor ioy, nor paine, but this life here.</l>
               <l>The weake ones
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anting grace ſtreight follow this,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Credulitie</hi> in ill, robbs man of bliſſe.</l>
               <l>Man wrongs his <hi>Maker</hi> by his want of merit,</l>
               <l>Sinne giues a ſharpe edge to a <hi>Satyrs</hi> ſpirit.</l>
               <l>Pyde <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anitie,</hi> th'inticing bayte for Fooles,</l>
               <l>Muffles our <hi>Knowledge,</hi> to intrappe our Soules.</l>
               <l>The world growne Aged, ſhould prepare to end,</l>
               <l>But Nature ſo gainſt reaſon doth contend.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:31"/>
               <l>As Light of Knowledge is put out by time,</l>
               <l>And to be vertuous now is held a crime.</l>
               <l>For thoſe ſeuen Sciences their grounds of Arts,</l>
               <l>Haue euermore poſſeſt their ſacred parts.</l>
               <l>Which ſeuen wide ſteppes vnto Damnation,</l>
               <l>Deciph'red are in order one by one.</l>
               <l>Firſt, Selfe-lou'd <hi>Pride,</hi> the Idoll of the Court,</l>
               <l>Is <hi>Plutoes</hi> Agent dreſt to make him ſport.</l>
               <l>And that miſ-ſhapen Monſter <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is his ſworne Taſter to the <hi>Furies</hi> meſſe.</l>
               <l>Next horrid <hi>Murder,</hi> makes his veynes to ſwell,</l>
               <l>And is as <hi>Butcher</hi> to the King of Hell.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Couetouſneſſe</hi> is his chief'ſt Officer,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Enuie</hi> forreine-States Interpreter.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sloath</hi> is his Chamber-groome, and makes the Bed</l>
               <l>To <hi>Lust,</hi> his Sodomitick <hi>Ganymed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Pluto</hi> ſpends the <hi>TIME</hi> amidſt thoſe Reuills,</l>
               <l>That firſt for pleaſure were deuiz de by Diuells.</l>
               <l>Who ſurfetting at length, made drunk with myrth,</l>
               <l>Caſts vp thoſe <hi>Monſters</hi> to defile the Earth</l>
               <l>That with weake <hi>Frailtie,</hi> lickes thoſe vomits vp,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Plutos Nectar,</hi> which muſt fill his Cuppe.</l>
               <l>Theſe Helliſh Stateſ-men, theſe foule-killing ſinnes,</l>
               <l>To follow here on Earth who ſo beginnes.</l>
               <l>And meanes to practiſe, as they come but neare him,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Well may hee know GOD, but hee cannot feare him.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Trahit ſua quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oluptas.</head>
               <l>HOwle on yee <hi>Satyrs,</hi> whilſt I ſit and marke,</l>
               <l>How woluiſh-Enuie at my <hi>Muſe</hi> doth barke.</l>
               <l>Backbite, detract, rayle, ſlaunder, and reuile,</l>
               <l>With words of hatred and vnciuill ſtile.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:32"/>
               <l>Firſt comes a Stateſman to the <hi>Stationer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And many better Bookes hee paſſing ouer,</l>
               <l>By chaunce findes this, whereon he reades a while,</l>
               <l>Then bytes the lippe, then frownes, then giues a ſmile,</l>
               <l>And to the <hi>Seller</hi> ſayes ſuch fiery braines,</l>
               <l>Should warme the priſon to reward their paines.</l>
               <l>Becomes it any man of his profeſſion,</l>
               <l>Reproue vs of our manners or tranſgreſſion?</l>
               <l>Away goes hee; Next comes my gallant Dycer,</l>
               <l>His ordinarie ſtomacke is more nicer,</l>
               <l>Who asks for new Books; this the <hi>Stationer</hi> ſhowes him:</l>
               <l>Streight ſweares t'is nought vnles the Poet knows him.</l>
               <l>Nor will hee read a Line: this <hi>Fortunes</hi> Mynion,</l>
               <l>Likes for ſooth nothing but his owne opinion.</l>
               <l>The mending Poet takes it next in hand,</l>
               <l>Who hauing oft the Verſes ouer-ſcand.'</l>
               <l>O filching ſtreight, doth to the <hi>Stationer</hi> ſay,</l>
               <l>Heer's foure lines ſtolne from forth my laſt New-play.</l>
               <l>And that hee'l ſwere euen by the <hi>Printers</hi> Stall,</l>
               <l>Although hee knowes tis falſe hee ſpeakes in all.</l>
               <l>Then comcs my <hi>Innes-of-Court-Man,</hi> in his Gowne,</l>
               <l>Cryes <hi>Mew,</hi> what <hi>Haekney,</hi> brought this wit to towne.</l>
               <l>But ſoone againe my gallant Youth is gon,</l>
               <l>Minding the <hi>Kitchin</hi> more then <hi>Littleton.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tut, what cares hee for Law, ſhall haue inough,</l>
               <l>When's Father dyes, that Cankard <hi>Miſer</hi>-Chuffe.</l>
               <l>Put him a <hi>Caſe</hi> in <hi>Ploydon</hi> then who will,</l>
               <l>That being his, plod you on Law-Bookes ſtill.</l>
               <l>Next comes by my <hi>Familiar,</hi> yet no Spirit,</l>
               <l>Who forceth me his Friendſhip to inherit.</l>
               <l>He ſees my Booke in Print, and ſtreight hee knowes it,</l>
               <l>Then asketh for the Booke, and the Boy ſhowes it.</l>
               <l>Then reades a while and ſayes, I muſt commend it,</l>
               <l>But ſure, <hi>Some Frend of his</hi> for him hath pend it.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:32"/>
               <l>He cannot write a Booke in ſuch a faſhion,</l>
               <l>For well I wote t'was nere his Occupation.</l>
               <l>Beſides by <hi>Checquer-Clarks,</hi> that oft haue ſeene him,</l>
               <l>I nere could heare of Schollerſhip was in him.</l>
               <l>Twere good to poze him but to haue it knowne,</l>
               <l>Or t'is no matter, let it euen alone.</l>
               <l>Next after him, your Countrey-Farmer viewes it,</l>
               <l>It may be good (ſaith hee) for thoſe can vſe it.</l>
               <l>Shewe mee King <hi>Arthur, Beuis,</hi> or Syr <hi>Guye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe are the Bookes he onely loues to buye.</l>
               <l>Well, that he likes and walkes. Then comes a Diuell,</l>
               <l>With ſober countenance, and Garments ciuill.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Puritane,</hi> or pure one, chooſe you whether,</l>
               <l>(For both as one makes ſelfe-ſame ſenſe together.)</l>
               <l>Hee lookes on ſome, and finding this the next,</l>
               <l>With very ſight therof his minde is vext.</l>
               <l>Fye ont't (ſaith he) that any man ſhould buye,</l>
               <l>Such Bookes prophane of fained Poetrie,</l>
               <l>That teacheth vice, worſe then your Playes on Stages,</l>
               <l>And is a ſhame to olde and future Ages.</l>
               <l>To louing Brother-hoods Communitie,</l>
               <l>That are defilde by ſuch impuritie.</l>
               <l>Away retires my fained <hi>Publican,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And after him next comes my Seruing-man.</l>
               <l>Who calls for new Bookes, heres one ſayes the Boy,</l>
               <l>He reads, and tells him, tut, this is a toy,</l>
               <l>And nere will pleaſe our Maides that take delight,</l>
               <l>In bookes of Ladies or ſome valiant Knight.</l>
               <l>Thoſe wittie workes buyes hee, and thence he paſſes,</l>
               <l>Next him comes my <hi>Scholaris,</hi> mongſt thoſe
<hi>Aſſes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who ſcarce vouchſafes his eyes thereon to glance,</l>
               <l>Or reading but a line or two by chance.</l>
               <l>Muſt on it ſtreight way ſtriue to breake a ieſt,</l>
               <l>(As who ſhall know hee's wiſer then the reſt.)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:33"/>
               <l>His wit that made this, well may begge by Pattln,</l>
               <l>Ile nere allow that good which hath no <hi>Lattin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beſides, how euer I diſdaine to read him,</l>
               <l>Vnles I knew what <hi>Houſe</hi> or <hi>Colledge</hi> bred him.</l>
               <l>Lo thus my <hi>Batchellour</hi> of little Artes,</l>
               <l>Will needes (preſage t'is naught) and ſo departs.</l>
               <l>At length comes-by my <hi>Mungrell</hi> home-ſpun Clarke,</l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>Antique</hi> geſture I beſeech you marke.</l>
               <l>No ſooner this my <hi>Booke</hi> in hand he ſeeth,</l>
               <l>But rubs his elbow, ſhowes his butter teeth,</l>
               <l>And ſayes, Is't Engliſh? then let him alone,</l>
               <l>For other language (tells you) learnt he none.</l>
               <l>But knowes by whome this <hi>Epigram</hi> was made,</l>
               <l>Hee's iuſt ſaith hee a man of mine owne Trade.</l>
               <l>Then on the ſudden falls his courage downe,</l>
               <l>Finding a Clarke tranſlated from a Clowne.</l>
               <l>Which hauing read, n'ere asks him how they ſell,</l>
               <l>But ſteales away, and ſhames to bid <hi>Farewell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Laſt comes my ſcoffing Friend of ſcowring wit,</l>
               <l>Who thinks his iudgement boue all Arts doth ſit.</l>
               <l>He buyes the <hi>Booke,</hi> and haſtes him to the
<hi>Play,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where, when he coms, and reads, Heer's ſtuffe doth ſay.</l>
               <l>Becauſe the lookers on may hold him wiſe,</l>
               <l>He laughs at what he likes, and then will riſe,</l>
               <l>And takes <hi>Tobacco;</hi> Then about will looke,</l>
               <l>And more diſlike the <hi>Play,</hi> then of the
<hi>Booke.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At length is vext hee ſhould with charge be drawne,</l>
               <l>For ſuch ſlight ſights to lay a Sute to pawne.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Number more</hi> like <hi>Addle</hi> braines as theſe,</l>
               <l>I could giue Phyſicke to for their diſeaſe.</l>
               <l>But better ſubiects ſhall employ my penne,</l>
               <l>Then the Low-minded muddy droſſe of men,</l>
               <l>That wrong our labours by their duller ſpirits,</l>
               <l>And iudge vs by their hate, not by our merits.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:33"/>
               <l>I taxe no one particular with crimes,</l>
               <l>That can finde fault at my <hi>Satyricke</hi> Rimes.</l>
               <l>Good men will loue mee, whiles the bad I loſe.</l>
               <l>Hee that ſpeakes alwayes truth, is ſure of Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Sic Tranſit gloria Mundi.</head>
               <l>MArke &amp; you loue me, who's yond marching hither,</l>
               <l>Some braue <hi>Low-countrey-Captain,</hi> with his feather</l>
               <l>And high-Crownd-hat, ſee into <hi>Paules</hi> he goes,</l>
               <l>To ſhowe his Doublet and <hi>Italian</hi> Hoſe.</l>
               <l>The whiles his <hi>Corporall</hi> walkes th'other Ile,</l>
               <l>To ſee what ſimple Gulls he can beguile,</l>
               <l>In hope of purchaſe, for if ſuch he meet,</l>
               <l>They follow muſt his <hi>Captaine</hi> through the Street.</l>
               <l>Where the poore Gulls before this Leader ſtand,</l>
               <l>With lowly reuerence, and their Hats in hand.</l>
               <l>Houering an Idoll, for true worth it ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he keeps him braue with wrong got-pelfe.</l>
               <l>But note this Gallants <hi>Genealogie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then ſhall you ſee his byrth and progenie.</l>
               <l>His Father liu'd by gaming to defraude,</l>
               <l>His Mother was an Ale-wite and a Bawde.</l>
               <l>Yet doth this <hi>Outſide</hi> ſo deceyue mens ſight,</l>
               <l>As oftentimes hee's taken for a Knight.</l>
               <l>But Farewell <hi>Captaine,</hi> and now note this man,</l>
               <l>This griping <hi>Mammon</hi> that doth all he can</l>
               <l>To bee on Earth Great <hi>Plutoes-Treaſurer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And when he dies, in Hell an Officer.</l>
               <l>This Slaue in <hi>Caſh</hi> hath forty thouſand pound,</l>
               <l>Yet ſuch a wretch there breaths not on the ground.</l>
               <l>His Parents in their liues, gaue him their ſtate,</l>
               <l>But he returnd their loues with matchleſſe hate.</l>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:34"/>
               <l>That like a <hi>Pellican</hi> to doe him good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>He nouriſht was by ſucking of their blood.</l>
               <l>And now poſſeſt of all they had before,</l>
               <l>Vnnaturally againſt them ſhuts his Dore.</l>
               <l>Yet now this Monſter liues to doe more euill,</l>
               <l>Lurking here ſtill a <hi>Ledger</hi> for the Diuell.</l>
               <l>The next to him comes <hi>Prodigalitie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Towneſmans Heire ſtrowting in brauerie.</l>
               <l>This Foole makes Suppers for Whores, Bawds, &amp; Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</l>
               <l>Yea, lends them money, but to call them Debtors.</l>
               <l>Nere lookes to hate' againe: Couſnage defeat him,</l>
               <l>When he wants Money at his neede, they beate him.</l>
               <l>No wonder, for hee more deſerues by halfe,</l>
               <l>Tis good enough for ſuch a golden Calfe.</l>
               <l>Of whom a man may trulie propheſie,</l>
               <l>His ende will be diſeaſed <hi>Beggerie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Next a penurious <hi>Miſer</hi> wretch comes forth,</l>
               <l>That owes his bellie more then he is worth.</l>
               <l>Yea, faine would feede out of the Priſoners basket,</l>
               <l>Wert not for feare, or ſhame, he durſt not aske it.</l>
               <l>Yet hath his Shoppe and Cellers ſtufft with Wares,</l>
               <l>Which to make profite of hee onely cares.</l>
               <l>Nere breakes the intereſt that thence redounds,</l>
               <l>But is as prouident in pence as pounds.</l>
               <l>Who to ſaue charges faine would woolward goe,</l>
               <l>But that he doubts the world thereof ſhould know.</l>
               <l>Tut, penny ſau'de (ſaith hee) is penny got,</l>
               <l>Spend they that meane to begge, I like it not.</l>
               <l>If labour or preuention can it let,</l>
               <l>Heel' not in <hi>Fleete</hi> or <hi>Counter</hi> lye for Debt.</l>
               <l>No, no, ſuch Husbands as are worldly wiſe,</l>
               <l>Will ſpend no more then nature ſhall ſuffiſe.</l>
               <l>As not to drinke more then their braynes can carie,</l>
               <l>For feare their iudgements from their wits ſhould varie.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:34"/>
               <l>A thouſand Cautions more hee might inferre,</l>
               <l>To make him proue a damned Vſurer.</l>
               <l>Adding ſtill Intereſt to the principall,</l>
               <l>Till in the ende hee hang himſelfe for all.</l>
               <l>But note what ſober Citizen comes next,</l>
               <l>That like a Preacher will expound a Text.</l>
               <l>And tell what danger comes by doing euill,</l>
               <l>Speake like a Saint, and doe worſe then a Diuell.</l>
               <l>For Golde heel' wrong his Father, cheat his Brother,</l>
               <l>And yet theſe faults reproues hee in an other.</l>
               <l>Who vnder cloake of Ciuill pollicie,</l>
               <l>Preſumes to couer all his villanie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pluto</hi> takes pride to ſee theſe plants ſo flouriſh,</l>
               <l>Who as his Children hee deſires to nouriſh,</l>
               <l>And takes them home when they haue ſpent their prime</l>
               <l>Leaſt tarrying long they ſhould corrupt more time.</l>
               <l>But wherefore rippe I vp thoſe dregges of men,</l>
               <l>That wrongs true labour and a <hi>Satyrs</hi> pen.</l>
               <l>To treat of <hi>Warres</hi> or Actions to be done,</l>
               <l>Let next the Current of your Channells runne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>¶ A Paradox in praiſe of Warre.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PEACE</hi> thou Corrupter of Mortalitie,</l>
               <l>Mother of ſhame and baſe ſecuritie.</l>
               <l>Whoſe beggerd wombe ſo many Baſtards brings,</l>
               <l>Three parts muſt ſtarue, the reſt like demie Kings,</l>
               <l>Raigne 'ore their Brothers, all maligne their byrth,</l>
               <l>To haue one Father, yet are Slaues on Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Aide mee ye powers, whoſe influence got you Fame,</l>
               <l>To rippe the wombe of peace, and ſhewe her ſhame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peace</hi> makes a faire ſhowe, but tis fowle within,</l>
               <l>Peace like to Riuers, feedes a Sea of ſinne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:35"/>
               <l>Let <hi>Warre</hi> in Forraine Lands hunt drowzie
<hi>Peace.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in a iuſt cauſe mans renowme increaſe.</l>
               <l>T'is wholſome <hi>Warre</hi> diſſolues the courſe of ſinne,</l>
               <l>Men beſt repent, when dangers neere beginne</l>
               <l>To ſhew their Faces'; but whiles peace doth hold,</l>
               <l>Our ſtrength is weake, and our Deuotion cold.</l>
               <l>Safety from worldly danger makes men thinke,</l>
               <l>They that ſtand faſt on earth ſhall neuer ſinke.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Countrey-Myſer</hi> that his gold preſerues,</l>
               <l>To feede him fatte whiles many thouſand ſtarues,</l>
               <l>Is thus occaſiond by this ſlothfull peace,</l>
               <l>Which leſſens vertue to make vice increaſe.</l>
               <l>T'is ſeareleſſe <hi>Peace</hi> makes pleaſure mans chiefe God,</l>
               <l>We want both ſight and feeling of <hi>Warres</hi> rodde.</l>
               <l>That Land more happie is that <hi>Warre</hi> doth nouriſh,</l>
               <l>Cauſing the world in better ſtate to flouriſh.</l>
               <l>For danger makes vs feare a ſudden ende,</l>
               <l>Feare ſaddes the ſoule becauſe it did offend.</l>
               <l>The feare of danger makes each man prepard,</l>
               <l>And of his ill paſt life to haue regard.</l>
               <l>Danger calls Conſcience to a ſtrict account,</l>
               <l>Repentance makes a heauie ſoule to Mount.</l>
               <l>Tis ſoft ſecuritie lulls men in ſinne,</l>
               <l>That onely couet but Earths ioyes to winne.</l>
               <l>Tis idle <hi>Peace</hi> that breedes in vs ſuch faction</l>
               <l>As kills at home, for want of Forraine action.</l>
               <l>The Valiant man doth hence his <hi>Fame</hi> increaſe,</l>
               <l>Maintaines himſelfe by warres, growes poore by peace!</l>
               <l>Hence flowes the fountaines of detected vice,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sloath, Lust, Deceipt,</hi> and filthie
<hi>Auarice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Extortion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurie,</hi> and gaines
<hi>Exceſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Gryping the Liuing of the <hi>Fatherleſſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So they by vſe or fraude their bagges may fil.</l>
               <l>In ſhow of goodnes they'l commit all ill.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14401:35"/>
               <l>Cheat their owne Brother to gaine worldly droſſe,</l>
               <l>And make them poore by Law, that ſuch dares croſſe.</l>
               <l>For this all-wiſhing-<hi>Golde</hi> is of that force,</l>
               <l>As muffles <hi>Iustice,</hi> and exiles <hi>Remorce.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Golde</hi> in theſe times can turne the wheele of
<hi>Fate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And make them beſt belou'd deſerues moſt hate.</l>
               <l>Golde can make peace ioyne hands of deadly Foes,</l>
               <l>Gold can make warre again wound peace with blowes:</l>
               <l>T'is peace that makes this <hi>Indian Golde</hi> ador'd</l>
               <l>This golden Calfe Idolatrizde, abhor'd.</l>
               <l>Golde in the ſoule breedes ſuch an alteration,</l>
               <l>As men deſire it more then their ſaluation.</l>
               <l>Some cut mens throats for Golde, commit all euils,</l>
               <l>Gold makes them Gods on Earth, and in Hell Diuels.</l>
               <l>T'is purſie Peace that makes it of ſuch price,</l>
               <l>And is the Mother of all ſinne and vice.</l>
               <l>Making vs prone to all ſecuritie,</l>
               <l>Which thus proceedes through times ſecuritie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peace</hi> makes Religion faint, and not regarded,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue</hi> a Beggar, <hi>Learning</hi> vnrewarded.</l>
               <l>Strange new Damnations, drowzie <hi>Peace</hi> beginnes,</l>
               <l>And now the world well knowes the worſt of ſinnes,</l>
               <l>Which through ſecuritie doe ſo increaſe,</l>
               <l>As endleſſe plagues are matched ſtill with Peace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plura ſequerentur.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>The faults eſcaped in the Printing (or any other omiſſion) are to be excuſed, by reaſon of the Authors abſence from the Preſſe, who thereto ſhould haue giuen more due inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Which the rather was neglected becauſe the Booke (beeing long ſince finiſhed) is as you ſee but lately publiſhed. Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the reſt (not leaſt to be reformed) in the last leafe of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams, in ſtead of the word Ballocks,</hi> read <hi>Ballackths, and in ſteed of hauing,</hi> read
<hi>ſauing. Beſides other ſcurrilities, which ſhould haue bene left out.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14401:36"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
